Camera's off. Mic's muted.
>> Uh,
I find the right thing. All right,
camera's off. Uh, share screen
and
>> I'm already recording.
I'm a tuple with Gabo because he likes
to draw.
If he's around,
>> he is for me. He's on for me.
>> All right, Luke. It is
>> second try.
All right, somebody answers the call.
Okay, now Lucas gets double vision.
Okay, and now got waking up.
Okay,
so my intention here is to mainly talk
about the more advanced or odd or things
you might not realize things about state
charts. Um, but I'm going to do a real
quick
uh overview for those of you who haven't
done much with them. And then of course
after we're done talking here, there's a
um
uh set of exercises that already stuck
on the Slack dev channel that you can
clone and and uh work on that have
solutions. So you can work on the
exercises, you make the test pass. As I
mentioned earlier, you might want to set
a time limit for each exercise. And if
you're not getting it, just go to the
solution and and understand it. Okay, so
quick review just kind of terminology
and what these things look like. So
state charts have been around since the
80s. Uh they were defined academically
by a guy named Herell. Uh and then they
sort of evolved from there. He did a few
years of research on refining them and
then in the 90s they got pretty widely
adopted uh and ended up in the worldwide
web consortium's set of standards and so
that standard is what I based the focal
logic implementation on. So it has the
exact semantics and and
behavior of state charts as defined by a
well- definfined standard that has
semantics and you know everything's just
really well defined. So if you have any
question about how things are supposed
to operate, you can just go look at the
standard in W3C
and see terminology wise a state chart
has uh states and transitions. Those are
the main things. It's got other things
called executable content as well. And
the states themselves are hierarchical.
So this distinguishes them from state
machines, finite state machines where in
finite state machines, they're flat. You
have a thing that has a bunch of states
and you can transition from one to the
other. Uh but they aren't nested.
So in a state chart, you have what's
called a compound state. That's a state
that contains other states. And I really
don't like the fact that I can't point
at my slides here. So, I think I'm just
going to do it in this mode. Uh,
maybe turn off
>> maybe share
>> slide only.
>> I'm just trying to get rid of these.
There we go. That's good enough.
>> Now I can point
because I just want to be able to
highlight things, things like that.
Right.
>> A state that has no children is
typically called a leaf or atomic state.
And all the states have a unique ID. In
fact, every node in a state chart has an
ID whether or not you give it one. If
you don't give it one, then it invents
one. Um, there's a little side note I
I'll make on that. The uh if you
re-evaluate a state chart in your ripple
and you have nodes that that have not
been given an explicit ID, their ids
will morph.
So that can cause in in rare cases it
can cause weird behavior because the ids
of of internal things change. Go ahead
whoever raised their hand.
>> If a state say chart has no ID, how do
you like point to it then?
>> No, no, no. The state chart itself has
session IDs. That's separate. The states
are the only thing that you know you
probably have to give IDs to because
that's the thing you target with a
transition.
>> Yeah, that's what I was saying. Oh, so
you're saying the state
>> I'm saying transitions have an ID. On
entry nodes have an ID. Every node in
the state chart has an ID whether or not
you choose to assign it one.
>> Okay. Uh a a good reason for assigning
uh IDs to every node is because then
debugging messages make a lot more sense
because you can tell which node is being
talked about when it says transition and
it gives you some randomly generated ID.
Move to blah. If you had given it an ID,
then you'd know which one it was. Uh
without assigning it an ID, you have to
guess.
Other questions on that?
>> No, that's that's
>> Yeah, I I guess that's we have some
tests
>> for our state charts. I think some
integration test that fail like if you
reload the expressions
>> that's fail.
>> That's that's an example. Yeah, that's
an example where the IDs being auto
assigned can cause
uh erratic behavior that you may not
expect. Yeah.
>> Okay. Yeah.
>> Uh
>> as a side note, as part of this
implementation, this top level node
actually takes this tree because this
each one of these functions just emits a
map or a vector of maps. Um, and this
top level thing pulls all these out of
the tree and normalizes them just sort
of like folk normalizes a folk database
so that the logic can look these up
easily. So if you look at the actual
state chart data structure that this
returns
uh it's got indexes in it, it's got the
the nodes normalized. It's got it's got
a bunch of extra stuff in it. Um even
though this this kind of state here this
is this is actually just nested maps
it's just a big nested data structure.
Um so that's just an internal
implementation detail. The other thing
you need to know as a term is the term
configuration
because state charts can have more than
one active state. Instead of saying the
state chart is in state blah, you say
the state chart has configuration and
the configuration is a set of all of the
states that are active. And the set will
always include the topmost state and
then the path down to the leaf. Right?
So if we're in the detail state, we're
also in the dashboard state and we're
also in the app state.
Go ahead.
Um what if like there are several
like agents like let's say parallel
states would they all be configuration?
>> We'll talk about parallel here a little
bit but yes the the short answer to your
question is yes
>> all active all active states go in the
set.
>> So one other question then is that is
that like an ordered set from top down
or is it just unordered? Uh that's a
great question actually. The um uh there
are ordered sets in state chart logic in
terms of evaluating things and the order
is document order.
Um I don't know if if uh focal logic
state charts reports this set in that
order. I don't think it does. It just
gives you a set. These are the states
that are active. But when evaluating the
chart internally, it actually does use
uh sets and their sort order is document
order because that's how the standard
specifies it
others.
Um, I was going to ask how useful is
this for parallel agents or maybe you
can answer it when we get there because
like
>> Well, okay. So, there's a difference
between parallel state charts and
parallel regions,
right? You can run any number of state
charts simultaneously in a system. Those
are all running in parallel. And of
course, their configurations are all
different because they're different
sessions.
So I assume you're talking about the
idea of a parallel node
>> which creates sub regions and in a
parallel node every immediate sibling is
active simultaneously
so they'll all be in the set.
>> Okay.
>> Was there another one or was that it?
>> That's all.
>> Okay.
events and basic transitions. We're
going to go into these in more depth
later, but I just wanted this is just
review. Um, events are represented in
this library as keywords. In the
official standard, event names are just
a dot tokenized
uh uh
um
a dotepparated token sequence. So like
without the colon, right? So in the
standard they look like that. And since
in closure we represent these kinds of
things as keywords, we represent them
with the colon in front. I made one
extension
to the standard here and that's that uh
slash acts like a dot as far as
tokenization goes.
Right? Does everybody know what I mean
when I say tokenization?
Like breaking apart into pieces.
So this has one token login. This has
two tokens, error and network. And this
has two tokens, error and network.
Go ahead with the question if that
didn't answer it.
>> Okay. So, you're saying the error.net
network in your library is exactly the
same thing as error network.
>> Yes. Slash and dot are are treated
interchangeably in terms of tokenizing
uh the event names. And we'll get to why
that's important here in a minute. Some
of you probably already know.
Events can carry an arbitrary map of
data. It's just a closure map. And
events can actually have a type,
internal or external. And again, we'll
we'll get to those in in a bit in terms
of the difference between how they how
they uh run. Uh the difference between
the two. Uh but the short the short
thing is that a raise node in the chart
is an internal event and external events
are placed on the queue with a send. So
there's an external event Q.
Right? So there's actually two event
cues in state charts.
Transitions are how you get from state
to state. Transitions uh match an event.
They can also be eventless, right? So
the event part is optional.
They can optionally have a guard
um uh and the guard is just a condition
that has to be true for the transition
to be what's called enabled.
They have uh optional target and the
target can be plural. This has to do
with parallel states that that Jeremy's
been referring to. We'll talk about that
in a moment. Like where should the
transition go? Doesn't have a target.
It's there just to respond to uh uh an
event.
Is the event optional? I may be
misremembering that transition can be a
Can a transition be eventless? I believe
it can. It just fires if its guard is
true.
>> Yeah.
>> Yeah. I I think it's correct.
>> No, that's absolutely true. Um these can
contain executable content children.
Executable content as a reminder are
things like on entry, onexit, script. Uh
there's also uh ones I added recently
that are part of the standard that I
hadn't added yet. If else raise. So any
node that tells the chart to do
something to the world, either modify
the data model, run a side effect, uh
send a delayed event to the state chart
at some later time. All that's
considered executable content.
And then these have an internal external
type which means something different
than the internal or external type of
event. Same word different meaning. And
we'll talk about the semantics of
internal versus external on transitions
when we get to that.
Um
any questions on the basics though?
Okay.
What I wanted to insert in here that I
didn't have time to to make a slide for
and I'll just go and show you in the
source code is that the state charts
library uh my state chart library uh
tries to abstract out all the possible
things that you might want to replace
depending on your execution environment
uh for your state charts. So state
charts have the idea that you can store
some data locally to the chart that the
chart can manipulate or read as it runs.
And there there are two basic things
really three three basic things you can
do with a data model. At startup you can
load data from someplace
right. So, so there's a node you can put
in the in the in the chart near the top
that says you want data to be
initialized in some way. Uh, the data
model protocol lets you abstractly
define how you get to that and load it,
right? So, you might, you know, you
might load a an Eden file from disk,
right? That sort of thing. Uh, or you
might have them colllocate the the data
that they want to supply right there on
the node. uh but ba basically the
standard says there should be some way
for the data model element in the
machine to pull in some initial data
into the data model. You need to be able
to retrieve the current data get
something at a path where the path is a
vector of keywords with an arbitrary
meaning that you define in the data
model and a way to update that data
uh via data operations. I made this
operation based so that you could extend
the data operations on the data model uh
to do more interesting things like you
know folk apply action that sort of
thing. Uh so so this makes the data
model completely pluggable. Uh and this
is also how we do things like on our our
uh
uh server side state charts. Uh we're
we're able to persist the data model
that the state chart is tracking into an
SQL database.
We have an event Q. This is for the
external event Q. So again in the um in
the fulcr integration of state charts,
the external event Q is implemented just
as a core async thing that just runs as
a local threadlike thing in your app. on
our server side state charts in Dao. Our
event Q on the server is actually
implemented as an SQL table and
algorithms around being able to send
them and process them.
the execution model. The idea here is
that in the expression say in a script
tag uh you might want in say a front end
state chart you might want the user to
be able to provide JavaScript
uh as their expression just as a string
uh or you might want the user to be able
to supply closure as a string that you
execute with say sigh
uh or you might want an execution model
where they just hand you lambdas. So the
idea here is you can plug in uh an
alternative for running the executable
nodes. Uh where the the notation on the
executable node can be anything you
wanted to define it to be. Uh as long as
you can write something that can run
those expressions. Uh on all of our
state charts at the Tao, we all just use
CLJC expressions, right? These are just
lambdas. Uh so this execution model is
pretty simple.
the processor protocol has to do with
running the actual algorithm itself. So
if you go and look at this W3C standard
for state charts, uh the current one I
think was written in September of 2015,
but there are multiple versions before
that at prior years. Uh so the state
chart standard evolved
um and since there's some possibility in
the future it might evolve again or
maybe you want to select the semantics
and and runtime behavior of an older
version because you like it better. This
allows you to plug in a different
algorithm for your state charts um uh
just by implementing this protocol.
Uh so this is this is intended right
we've got for example state charts in
dao that run for long periods of time
and you wouldn't want to change the
algorithm that those run internally.
So you can imagine that for dao you want
to pin the state chart processor to a
particular version of the algorithm even
if the library were to invent and define
another one. uh so in in keeping with my
desire to make my libraries 100%
backward compatible whenever possible
but allow for a forward you know a path
forward an easy path forward uh this
this allows you to have that right some
new version could come out I could
define the new algorithm and you can opt
into it at some later time if it works
for you better or not you can just keep
using the old one
uh there's an invocation processor So
this protocol has to do with the fact
that state charts define
uh a way to invoke other things.
Um the only invocation processor that's
usually required is one that can invoke
other state charts. Um but this is
allowed to invoke basically anything at
all. Uh you could have this invoke a web
worker on the front end in JavaScript
and run something in a thread that has
like a compile of solidity uh for
Ethereum's contracts or something,
right? It it doesn't have to be a state
chart. Uh basically the the interface
between state charts and an invocation
is that you can start it, you can
forward events to it from the parent
state chart and then it can do whatever
it wants with the events. You can stop
it because when an invocation is left in
a state chart, it's supposed to stop the
thing it invoked. Um and then you can
ask your list of invocation processors,
hey do you support this particular type
of invocation? Right. So this is
basically just discovery.
Any questions on that?
>> Are are we going to have like examples
on these? Because I I would like to I've
actually asked
um an AI to actually explore codebase so
it could explain it to me. Are you going
to are we going to run through any
>> We're going to run through some of this.
Uh invocations I'm not going to do in
great detail. Um
uh the the point of this little part of
the discussion is just to show you that
the design of the Fulcr is meant to be
very flexible which is why we can use it
in Fulcro and on the back end in
completely different use case kinds of
environments where one the back end runs
state charts that might run for years
and have to be reliable and the front
end runs state charts that maybe run a
wizard and if you reload the page All
right, you just reset all your state
charts, right? That sort of thing.
Um, so I'm just trying to give you the
ideas of of what's here that's that can
be manipulated, right? So this is less
about knowing how to manipulate it and
more just being aware that the ability
to manipulate it exists
or extend it exists. Does that make
sense?
Yeah, of course.
>> Okay. And then the last two are the
state chart registry. This is just where
do I store the definition of state
charts so that when I go to run an event
from a state chart that started a month
ago, right, I didn't keep that thing in
memory. Uh I need to be able to
reconstitute it from some sort of
storage. Um I need to be able to find a
state chart, right? That's essentially
what a state chart registry is about.
And then working memory store has to do
with uh actually this is the separate
concern. The data model up here was
reading and writing the data model. And
this down here has to do with being able
to store
uh uh everything about a given
uh session. So a state chart's running.
It has a configuration. It has a data
model. Uh and when the processor right
the thing that that has the algorithm in
it goes to process an event in order to
do that it needs the working memory
uh and the event and the working memory
includes
the type of thing that's running the
state chart um
definition the registry key. So this
process event this end contains all of
the different implementations of these
protocols. So it can find the data
model, it can find the event Q, it can
find right, it has all those things
available. Um so when you process an
event, it can look up any of these
protocols in the end
uh to run this event
starting from this current working
memory. get back the working memory and
then save it back to whatever store it's
stored in.
So the the the Tao loop say for the
server side processing is get the
working memory process it in the
processor which gives you back a new
version of the working memory and then
save it in the working memory that's
that's processing an event question
>> um I have two questions one about the
registry and the other about the working
memory store
>> so uh for the working memory store like
is this going to be saving for every
event or does it try to batch
>> no batching every event.
>> Isn't that um so is there any
performance concern or I don't know
>> um
is there a performance concern?
Typically not. So if if you were let me
give you the the two environments that
we run things in. Um so in the front end
uh your working memory is uh let's see
now what is it in in it's the actual app
database right it's the state map it's
it's it's actually normalized into the
focal state map so it's a swap on an
atom
>> right getting it is is a dref of the
atom saving it's a swap on the atom
that's very fast
uh so you can very easily run you know
many many many events per second uh
because it's all it's all just in memory
The server side state charts aren't
meant to run individual state charts
thousands of times a second. You're not
doing animation with them. You're doing
things like subscriptions where an event
maybe fires at most once a month. So, uh
the the performance of an individual
state chart isn't really a problem.
You've got to pull the working memory
from SQL, process the event, which maybe
has to create an invoice and talk to the
Dion, right? That could be a couple of
seconds,
right? Give you back the new working
memory. uh save that in SQL.
>> So
>> okay.
>> Yeah. Um a question was which protocol
is orchestrating this like because you
mentioned how different parts of this
are um pluggable likeable
>> using this protocol. So let's say a
person wants to do something where
whereby maybe um it fetches a bunch of
working memory in batch and you know
executes them and save them one at a
time like which protocol can
>> well you wouldn't do that. you you need
you need exactly one semantics and so
this actually gets fairly complicated.
Um
uh
oh
is this not indexed yet? All right so
we'll stay we'll stay here for the
moment. Um so for example uh let's say
you're talking about the server side
state charts right so in the front end
JavaScript single thread you run an
event to completion you're done you put
it back you let go of the thread
whatever happens happens but there's
only one thread right so so the idea of
batch processing and parallel processing
isn't even defined so let's talk about
the server where we do have the
possibility to to do things in parallel
um uh we have all sorts of state charts
in the system. And of course, the more
state charts you get, the more sessions
you get running, the more probability
that any given second you might have
lots of events to process. Let's say we
had a sale, right? And um a whole bunch
of people signed up and and got new
subscriptions, say a thousand of them,
all in the same day, all within a
relatively short period of time. That
would be a lot of parallel events to
process in potentially a relatively
short period of time where those events
because they're creating invoices and
doing side effects things like that each
event might take several seconds to run
right um early on the first
implementation of the SQL event Q into
Tyco for simplicity was single threaded
there was only one thread
um and then we discovered do you
remember this Nico I think you were
around some somebody was here here was
was around
uh we discovered that the state charts
like the subscriptions were running like
like 90 days behind something like that
some extremely crazy number
because the queue was so backed up from
that single thread trying to keep up
with them that it just couldn't keep up.
Um I don't know if it was quite that bad
but it it it was backed up quite a ways.
So we had to convert to a multi-threaded
processing
uh where where we process these in
parallel. And so then the rule is you
can't have two threads running an event
for the same session, right? That would
be two things that read the same working
memory, did different events, and then
tried to save back the working memory.
One would overwrite the other. That'd be
bad,
>> right? So we have a thread pool and then
we have a very complex sequence of
transactional logic and locking that
that ensures that any given thread uh uh
or no two threads will run an event for
the same session at the same time yet
will allow us to run as many s as many
non-equal sessions in parallel as we
have threads.
long answer but does that
>> answer your question basically?
Um yeah I I do so like um that custom
processing logic like which protocols
did you had to hook into or like provide
your own implementation in order to do
that
>> right and that's what I was trying to
show you here
>> that's on the base environment perhaps
>> is it in base end
>> like the file
>> that's like our proxy environment so you
can find everything there
>> yeah that's the environment but where's
where's the um process event. I was
going to show the actual loop.
>> Oh, the loop. That's an
event.
>> Is it here?
Yeah, this is it. This is what it looks
like.
And this is for delivering a synchronous
event. But the loop that that has all
the threads looks very similar to this.
So we obtain a lock for the session. We
create a transaction so that we either
do everything with respect to the state
chart in the database or it all gets
rolled back and it'll retry on a
separate try. Uh we get them working
memory which is just calling that
protocol get working memory. These are
just wrappers for mocking. Um we process
the event.
uh we record the fact that we did it
which is uh uh us updating the event
table. So this is where we store the
events that need to be delivered to say
that the event was delivered, right? So
we're setting the the delivered flag to
true here. So we won't redeliver the
event. This is why we need a transaction
is because we don't want to mark the
event delivered without actually saving
its working memory and vice versa. We
wouldn't want to save it or mark it.
Yeah, you get it. Um,
>> yeah,
>> right. And then if the state chart
finished, then we want to delete the
working memory out of the SQL table.
Otherwise, we want to resave the working
memory in the table. That's it. So, so
basically you just have a loop that that
that
looks for. In the case of delivering an
event synchronously where we're
recording the event in the table already
complete
and an event that was in the table, we
have a select that looks for the events
that aren't delivered whose time to
deliver has passed.
Right?
>> And then we just do this exact thing.
Get the working memory, process the
event, write it back.
>> Oh, I see. That's for the synchronous
event, right?
>> This one is synchronous. Yeah. Yeah. The
the loop is is somewhere else and we
don't need to look
>> the at the at the bottom is the same.
>> Yeah, there you go.
>> I guess the main point is that it's our
own process that is doing the processing
using the protocols. Exactly.
>> I was think maybe the fur library is the
one to do that and we need to override
another protocol to
>> you. You can't no you can't really do
this at the library level because you
need these kind of complex things to do
the to do the uh transactional semantics
of it.
>> Uh so rather than rather than define
that right that it just doesn't make
sense. It's it's too complex given what
data stores you select and what
semantics they have. Uh you may have to
do you know crazy back flips depending
on what you decide. And all I wanted to
do is make it so that uh if someone had
to defined a store you wanted to use and
someone had defined the processor that
you wanted to use etc. Uh you could plug
it in here and you right you you'd have
some chance of getting everything
>> right.
>> Okay.
And I had another question regarding the
history.
>> Um sure.
>> Do you mind going over what exactly it
is like? Um cuz I I'm also sort of
confused as to where the state chart is
uh stored and how I know the um UI state
machine is simply a map in which you can
get it and you know modify it and do
whatever but then I still struggle to uh
see the um state chart that way and you
mentioned it's inside the DB and I don't
know whether it's global state the
registry
>> right so when you define a state chart
it's just data and when you register it
you give it a global name typically a
namespaced keyword word um that puts it
in this registry. This is this is
typically like on the front end. This is
just a a map and an atom. That's all the
state chart registry is. Uh in our
backend uh uh state charts, it's also
that um
uh it's it's it's an in-memory
representation for looking things up. Uh
it's not actually persisted. This is so
you can right if we if we were to
persist the definition of the state
chart that would be hard to bug fix
them.
>> All right.
>> Right. But the runtime system needs to
be able to when it goes to process an
event. It needs to be able to find the
state chart. Right. I've got an event.
I've got a session ID. I've got the
working memory. The working memory tells
me which kind of like what's the state
charts registry key, but the code of it
isn't there, right? The data structure
isn't there. So this just gives it a
join point. This is just you saying
here's how I'm keeping track of the
state charts in my system and because I
can define them in any namespace. Um,
right? I I'm not going to go scan all
the name spaces for the state chart. I
just need someplace where you stored
them. So, you typically just use the
predefined atom based registry uh and
register them.
>> Yeah, I understand. Um there is I don't
know there's this other protocol that
has this um load method.
>> The one the data model. Yeah.
>> Yeah. The data model. So like uh is that
loading the registry or the
>> No, no, no, no, no, no. This is to
populate the data model of the state
chart. So the state chart can store
arbitrary data within it.
Right. This is where you can do an
assign executable content inside the
state chart to to put data in the state
chart itself in the session.
Load data is is meant for initial state
in the state chart. That's basically
what it's meant for. I don't think we
use it to be honest. I don't think we've
used it for any of our state charts.
Um
>> um I'm still a little bit confused. So
like when it loads the data, it returns
the initial working memory.
>> Uh no no. So the so the data model is
meant to store the data in the
processing end right where the
processing end
is is an abstraction. Uh in our case
well in all cases the processing end is
going to have the working memory of the
running session
and all an implementation of all these
protocols.
What load data is supposed to do is it's
supposed to copy whatever source
abstractly
says. Could be an expression, could be a
function for the processing model, could
be right, you define it because you're
defining the protocol. But the idea is
whatever you've specified in the source
that's declared on the data model
element of the state chart needs to be
copied into
the data of the processing end of that
session.
It's an initialization. That's all it
is.
I'm going to look at an example and see
whether I can fully understand it. I'm
still getting confused between this and
also the
>> So, so when when I what we got to Why
didn't that let me draw? There we go.
Um, we have we have the state chart
definition,
right? And so this is the rules to move
from state to state to state in a
system, right?
>> Yes.
>> We have any number of instances
that all kind of point to that
definition and say I'm a running
instance of these and these each have a
configuration.
>> Yes.
>> Right. What states we're in. They also
have data. Sort of think of like class
and instances. Right. This is the class.
This is an instance
and an instance of a class can have
private data.
That's what data models representing.
It's representing the fact that you can
hold on to some data that's specific to
your session and your session alone that
these state definitions can put data
into or pull data out of.
Right? It's just working data. It's like
variables for the state chart.
>> Okay. And this session this session data
is that what we are calling working
memory?
>> No, working memory is the combination of
both.
>> Ah okay.
Oh I see. So the combination of the
definition with the session data.
>> Exactly. The com the working memory has
the the pointer to the definition and
the current configuration and the
current working memory. That's what's or
the current data set. That's what's in
working memory.
>> Yeah, I see. I understand.
>> That help. So load data is when I start
up, what data should I put in here?
That's really all it's used for.
And in the XML version of um state
charts, I believe source is a URL.
You're telling it to load data from some
URL on the internet or whatever, right?
Or it can be a file name like load data
from this file.
Right? In closure that makes kind of
less sense. It makes more sense for
source to maybe be a map of data or
right some data structure that you can
just declare on this element.
But because I've made this abstraction,
you absolutely could load a file or a
URL or whatever. Source is completely
abstract here. It's whatever you want it
to be.
Okay, I understand.
>> Yeah. So that that that's part of the
problem is by making it this abstract,
it's hard to get your head around. Okay,
what do I put there? Well, depends on
what you define data model to be.
>> And um current data would be this
session data.
>> Current current data is just the way
your algorithms uh I didn't mean for to
erase it read the instance data.
>> Yeah.
>> Right. This is get a particular piece of
the instance data. This is get all of
it.
>> All right. So preferably if you want to
get All right. So we shouldn't like be
looking into the working memory
directly.
>> No, you really shouldn't. And and you
shouldn't be using this directly either.
This is something you could implement to
provide a data model, but your state
chart executable content is going to
indirectly cause these to be invoked
by the processing algorithm.
>> Yeah. Okay.
>> Right. So you're never going to you you
well I won't say never. You could pull
the data model out of the end in your
state chart script like your script. The
in has this data model in it. And so you
could call any of these methods on that
protocol. For example, update, right?
You could do an explicit update to the
data model or an explicit get at to the
data model, but you usually don't need
to because the current data is plopped
into one of the the elements of your
scripts arguments, your your lambda's
arguments as a convenience.
And then the ops you return call update
for you. So you don't have to.
So that's that's why you typically don't
use this directly. It's something you
could implement but it's something you
don't typically have to call.
>> Okay. I I think I understand everything
now.
>> Okay. Cool.
Okay. So anybody need a break? Bathroom
break. Drink break.
>> Sorry. I have a I have a quick question.
Yeah. just seeing the code in
uh process synchronous event in that
title.
>> Um yeah, deliver synchronous event. Um I
know we have these uh session logs and
with transactions, but I was wondering
if any of these have any timeouts built
into them.
>> With session lock has has definitely has
a timeout. Um with transaction, that's
the low-level SQL settings that you and
I did, right? uh the the max time idle
in lock that kind of thing.
>> Yeah. So that's that's that was the
cause of one issue. Exactly. A while
back and I changed it by 30 or 60
seconds.
>> Exactly. Yeah. It was set to a day.
Yeah.
>> I was wondering where that was. So
>> that was that was due to this with
transaction. I think actually it wasn't.
Uh there's a there's a select for update
and that's what was actually allocated
to lock.
over choosing the next event. Do you
mean?
>> Yeah.
>> This is kind of sad. This used to not
have the reddest thing on it because
this with transaction and the select for
update in the loop is supposed to
>> create uh what I needed with locks at
the database level, but for some reason
RDS in a multi-AZ
layout doesn't always honor the lock,
right? So, I had to add this red as crap
around it. What was the question?
>> Yeah, sorry. Very quick question going
on kind of Jeremy's stuff, right?
Because I'm asking questions.
>> Do AI while I'm while you're doing this
to catch up. So, the data model is like
what we we use like ops assign to like
>> Yeah. Okay. Cool.
>> Yep.
>> Cool. Cool. Cool. Well, and and here
here's the even kind of to me the cooler
thing is in the fulcro implementation,
the data model uh has both state chart
local values that get normalized into
their own table in the state map. Um but
it also has operations that will work on
the folk state map at its root level
which gives you the actor and alias
uh support. So the data model actually
supports the idea of working with
aliases that manipulate values of
particular components in the state
database.
Right? So that abstraction came in handy
in that sense.
>> Yeah, that that's a little bit abstract
for me. I would have to see some code.
Uh here I I'll so so when you do when
you do uh one of these ops like like ops
assign uh you're supposed to give uh I
forget exactly how this works but you're
supposed to give a path and a value.
This isn't necessarily the the exact
note of sign. I don't remember exactly
what you do here. I think maybe you
don't need the map. I think you just
give it a path and a value.
>> It looks like
>> yeah I think you can just say yeah it's
like uh user ID and ID. Yeah.
>> Yeah. Something like that. Right. Um
>> what I'm saying is the data model
interprets these paths. So I can say oh
well if you say folk
state a that means the root level key
and the fulcro map whereas this means
local to the session
get it.
>> Yeah. So you're you can manipulate
fullcross stuff with
>> Exactly. Yeah. So, so then if I put an
alias in here where I say, well, the
actor slashforms
uh right and that stands for an ident
and then this is UI busy.
>> Yeah. Okay.
>> Right. So now my data model abstracts
away the idea of where that goes. Right.
I just don't even have to worry about
it. It's just up. Yeah. On the form make
the busy flag true. Right.
>> So you have Okay. So, but but you have
so that vector thing though um is like a
nested path because like what I'm base
you can just put keywords too and I
guess that's just flat like one level.
>> Exactly. You put a single keyword. Yeah.
If you just put a keyword, then then
you're saying I just want the the the
root of the local
>> uh you know the local session data,
>> right?
>> So I I didn't know that like like Fulcro
has state charts built in to it just by
itself. It's not
>> no uh folk there the state charts
library has a folk integration set of
name spaces.
>> I got it. Got it.
>> Right. that have implementations of all
of these. So yeah, if you go to the
state charts library uh and and look at
the integration velcro
uh
operations hook, right? So these are
extended operations for like invoking a
remote, associating via an alias,
invoking a load.
Right? So I'm sort of this the the fact
that it's all protocol based and you
you've kind of got the ability to hook
into all this stuff lets you define you
know extend the the u
uh
list of operations that you can return
from an expression. And then if you look
at the
trying to find where the
installed state charts process events
where's the
it should be indef
type here we go focal data model. So
this is the data model implementation
for the fulker integration.
Um, so here source
is literally just a map,
right? And the map just gets swapped
into the local data area of the session,
right? Um, and then we force schedule a
render current data,
right? uh does this
you know resolving aliases and getting
the current state and that kind of
thing. Get at looks at the path tries to
figure out if the path says root then
that means just local data. If it's a
keyword all by itself then that's get
that keyword from local data etc. This
is just an implementation of the
protocol.
Not not not too difficult at all. And
then the update with a list of ops
actually uses a multimethod
so that this is extensible. you can
extend the operations that are supported
and the default just says I don't
understand what you want to do and then
the rest of them uh which are in this
file as well uh like delete for deleting
a particular key in the path does the
same path logic to figure out which
thing to dissoc from where
that clarified
Yeah.
>> And then I think if we look at other
depth types, right, there's the working
memory store,
right? So this is just storing at a
particular state chart ident
right get in swap
trivial like like really really simple
and then the
uh
the event Q I guess isn't
there is an external event Q I thought
it would be in the same
name space but maybe I put it over here.
Oh I reified it. So here's the event Q
which is using a real Q which oh is this
just using the manual pulled Q and it
starts an async loop on it.
I don't know where the loop is but
anyway you get the basic idea.
Um,
okay. Other questions on that.
That's good. We We've taken an hour to
get through four slides. There were
there were pent up pent-up demand for
questions.
>> How many slides are there?
>> 60.
>> We scheduled lots of time, right?
>> Yeah. We need we need a cool down just
to catch up on. So I guess we're going
to slide that.
>> Yeah. Yeah. Some a lot of these
questions that you've asked will make a
lot of these other things go fast.
Okay. So event matching this is the next
important thing to understand.
Okay. So first of all uh the event names
are meant to be hierarchical. So I
mentioned a moment ago that that in the
focal focal li focal logic library
slash counts as a tokenizer.
Uh but the the basic idea so this should
be dot and slash.
Uh the basic idea is that an event
matches
uh if the transition
if the transitions you know event value
tokens
uh uh include what the incoming event
lists. So if the transition says error
then that matches error error.end
error.s send.failed
error.s send/failed
uh etc.
If the transition event says error.s
sendin, that does not match an incoming
error event. So, it just kind of makes
sense, right? You've got you got this
idea that a transition can handle more
specific kinds of errors
um uh
as a default, right? Kind of as a fall
through.
And then here, this was actually a bug
in the prior version. So if you're
running an older version, this isn't
true. But
>> uh uh the it's it's tokenbased. So error
does not match errors because the right
it's it splits them at dots. Nico,
>> no. I I've seen like we also like in the
seen like error dot uh star that star
also works as a wild card after The star
acts as a wild card. Yeah. Yeah, that's
a great point. Uh for for clarity, you
can also specify it that way, but the
dot star just gets stripped by the
matcher uh on the transition. So, it's
it's there for an it's there for beauty
for you to sort of yes,
>> like make you really understand. I'm
trying to match other things besides
just error, but technically the state
chart library will match without it.
Uh, so the asterics must be at the end.
It's going to be like in the middle.
Correct. An intermediate token.
>> Correct. It's it's undefined if you put
it in the middle. I I can't tell you
what it would do. It would probably
strip it, tokenize it, and yeah, it
wouldn't work the way you want it to
work.
>> Uh, it's only it's only suffix suffix
based whatever. Uh, and of course, you
can use colon star as uh I'll match on
anything, but that's the same thing as
an eventless transition. So you can just
like leave the event off of the
transition and and you'll get that
behavior.
Okay. So that's how events are matched.
That doesn't mean which transitions will
go. That's just how event names are
matched.
>> Yep.
>> Okay. Now I'm going to jump to parallel
regions first because some of the other
things we need to talk about you need to
understand parallel first. And we
already talked a bit about them. They're
not really all that difficult, but there
are a couple of tricky things here.
Okay, so the idea of parallel is you
create what are what are known as
regions.
And a region is just it's just a state.
Um, and it's a state that's an immediate
child of a parallel element. That's
that's really what what the term region
means. Region is just a child immediate
child of a parallel element. That's a
state.
All of the regions in a parallel element
will be simultaneously active.
Another rule you need to remember is
that if a compound state which is a
state that contains other state is
active then one or one exactly one of
that compound states must be active.
And you can actually specify which one
with an initial.
Go ahead question.
>> Uh
I I I was going to jump into the
configuration line. The last line.
>> Oh yeah, it's wrong.
Oh, sorry. Uh,
yeah, it's it's not it's not got enough.
>> I thought it was missing app. Yeah,
>> it's missing app. Yes, thank you. It's
missing app. It's also missing boss and
it's also missing network.
>> I wasn't able to proofread all this.
Claude actually generated for them this
for me in co-work
uh
in in Keynote or in PowerPoint format
which was kind of cool. Um so I hadn't
had had a chance to go over everything
of the fine tooth comb but I spent
several hours just repromp not
reprompting but refining.
Okay does that clarify?
>> Yes.
>> Okay. So a parallel doesn't have an
initial because all of the states are
active. All the immediate children are
active. If initial isn't specified, it's
the first state, first child state in
document order. That's the default.
So couple rules there. You can specify
initial to point to a state that you
didn't list first as the initial. That's
also good protection if you're doing
silly things like moving forms up and
down in the state chart and sort of
reorder them and suddenly change how the
state chart acts. Um because it is right
it is document order uh execution.
Any questions about this?
>> Okay. Now there's Go ahead.
Uh, is it possible to conditionally only
start a um a subset of parallel states?
>> Nope. They all start.
>> Okay.
>> There's there's a correlary to that, but
we'll get to that in a second.
>> Or maybe the um let's say a person were
to implement I don't know is it a
processor? Can they do something like
that? I'm just asking like
theoretically.
>> No. So the semantics of a state chart
are well defined. So the algorithm
defines which of these states is active.
Um you could define a different
algorithm that would do different
things. Absolutely. That's pluggable. I
wouldn't recommend it because you'd have
to do all the research and thought about
how how that affects things. You're much
better off going with the the
wellressearched well thoughtout
multiples, right? I mean they they spent
decades refining this so that it it
represents
all the possible things they could think
of in terms of modeling systems.
Uh so it's it's usually a problem on the
part of your understanding and
simplification of the problem and not
not a problem of the way state charts
work.
>> Yeah. Yeah.
>> Okay. So when to use parallel versus
compound? This is pretty
straightforward, right? Compound states,
that's the earlier, you know,
hierarchical stuff we were looking at,
are mutually exclusive. Um, they're
nested. Uh, if you, if you have
siblings, only one thing can be active
at a time. Uh, transitions flow between
them, right? So, that's pretty
straightforward. You use parallel when
you have truly independent things. Now,
you could also ask, and this is a
perfectly reasonable question, why don't
I just define other state charts and
just run separate sessions.
Um, and that's true. If things are
completely truly orthogonal, you can
just run different state charts, right?
They're not going to interact with each
other at all. There's also the thing we
talked about earlier, invocations.
Invocations are serve kind of a sort of
different purpose. Um but but when you
want a single state chart to track
multiple concerns simultaneously that's
when you want peril. An example of this
that we're currently actively using in
the Brazil state charts or that actually
it's the routing system that of the
state charts library
uh is the idea of whether or not uh a
route is is well not not not busy
whether or not uh we should be showing
the user a reason for routing failing
for example a form saying hey I'm dirty
right that should prevent routing
and so So the the the
actual action of routing is blocked by a
conditional guard on the transition, a
wildcard tople transition that catches
all routing events. If something says
there's things are busy, then that
prevents route, but there's no user
feedback in that. The state chart just
enforces it, which is nice, right? You
don't leave the dirty form. Uh because
the state chart, right, with one line,
uh you can structure the the state
chart.
Um
where is it?
>> And that's a parallel state.
>> Yeah.
Right. So this this is a parallel node
and it has two children.
The routes
um uh are passed in. That's a whole
separate thing. But then the routing
inpost state is a state that basically
has two things. either I'm not showing
the user the fact that there's a problem
or I am showing the user that there's a
problem and if I'm showing it then the
user can tell me okay I understand or I
want to do it anyway throw away my
changes
right pretty straightforward it's very
simple little little region um and then
the emitted routes
uh
Hold on.
Uh has
>> uh hold on. I'm looking for the top
level
uh con route star.
Yeah, I'm making changes to my file.
Oh, I thought it was here. Basically,
the the uh routing system here emits a
top level transition that has a cond on
it that basically says if we're busy, we
do nothing. Oh, it's right here. I'm
stand I'm standing right on it. Right.
So, if there's a route to event and
we're busy, record where we wanted to go
and raise the show routing info.
So now that parallel region is now in
the show state or in the non idle state,
the open state, right? We've recorded
where the user wanted to go. So if they
click on the thing that says, "Yeah, go
there anyway," we can go there. Um or
they can just close the dialogue and
we've we've blocked the route right with
this condition with this one transition
uh at the top of the routes.
Does that make sense? You see that?
So it's like one region the route region
is sending events to the routing info
region that is al that is a part of the
>> yeah so the whole chart is getting
events like colon route to and then the
the
this is sort of like como
ui
you know foo form right that's the route
you want to go to right that's the event
that's coming in Um, and when you create
this, we're not using this particular
thing in Tao except in Brazil. Uh, uh,
when this when you generate the routes,
it automatically generates a bunch of
transitions for you that take these
events.
>> Right.
>> Right. But we put those here. These are
the direct transitions. These are these
transitions. So we put this one first
so that its wild card matches the the
the thing and if the condition is true
document order this is the transition
that's going to go. So we block this
transition from going because this one
matches first.
>> Right. So this
>> that one doesn't have a target. So
you're not changing to a different
state.
>> Exactly. We're not we're not letting it
move. We're not we're not moving from
the state we're in because we want to
stay on that route and the routes are
defined as states in the state chart.
Kind of cool, right? I mean, this is why
I wanted state charts as a routing
system
>> because you can model these these global
concerns that are typically kind of a
pain, right?
Okay. And when you when the user wants
to like force the routing like the
routing input is going to say show and
the user can just like force.
>> Exactly. Exactly. And that sets it up so
that this busy condition will evaluate
to false.
>> Ah
>> right. And this record failed route put
in the local data model where you wanted
to go. It put this event in there. It
saved the event basically.
Right. Assign failed route as the event.
It just saves the event. So that when
you force the route, it right the
override route sets it up so that it
sends the event and tells it force true
in the event data so that busy can see
that and say, "Oh, nope. I'm not busy."
And we're just rescending the same same
event.
>> Okay. Yeah, I was confused like why
parallel regions for that, but it's kind
of cool.
>> Why parallel regions? parallel regions
because there's two separate things
going on at the same time.
>> Yeah. Yeah. Exactly. Yeah. Yeah.
>> Yeah. I don't want to leave the form.
The form still needs to be the route,
but I need something that tells me I
should be open and receive events uh to
to react
to to whatever the user wants to do.
>> Yeah. Yeah, wherever that was.
>> Yeah, I also get because we said like
parallel it was like because two regions
were truly independent but one is
sending events to the other basically.
>> Well, all right. So, yeah, let's talk
about what truly independent means.
They're independent in the sense that uh
the the state of one
uh doesn't doesn't depend on the other.
So the fact that a form is busy
uh isn't our our our our popup that
shows hey that was busy do you want to
you know you've got unsaved changes.
Yeah,
>> right. That's an independent concern,
right? I'm just trying to notify the
user I denied routing. And denied
routing is an independent kind of thing
from any given form. They're not
connected in any way. I have a hundred
different forms. Any one of them could
say busy. Um, right.
>> Yeah.
>> And I don't I don't really need to know
anything about that form state. All I
need to know is that the condition of
the system is somehow busy is true.
So, so there's always some kind of
coupling, right? They're they're one
system.
So, truly independent doesn't mean
they're they're un untied in terms of
interaction. So, for example, let's
imagine uh you're trying to model in
state charts uh uh um
an uh a boom box, right? That has a
cassette player and a CD player and a
whatever, right?
>> Um the cassette player and it's also got
a clock, right? That show you what time
it is, right? Uh you could model the
clock and its buttons to set the time
and etc etc as a parallel region running
in the same boom box state chart
and uh you know the the uh uh volume
maybe is a piece of local data with
transitions that can move that data up
and down and the cassette deck has a
play and paused and right. So there's
there's definitely things that can be
happening kind of simultaneously
in the same state chart that could some
of which could be easily modeled as
parallel regions.
>> Uhhuh. That's cool.
>> Also, it's it's it's possible that your
parallel regions might want to respond
uh to the same event.
Uh so say for example um
>> trying to think of an of a good example
here. ah uh traffic lights, right?
You've got a pedestrian
crosswalk thing for east, west, and one
for north, south, and you've got the
traffic lights for east, west, and
north, south.
Um, and you have some sort of timed
events that are going to happen to say,
"Oh, well, it's time to warn the
pedestrians that are currently crossing
that they should hurry up. We're about
to change the light."
>> Right? And so uh uh you know that event
causes just one set of lights right
maybe the north south ones to start
blinking.
But then when you get the next event
uh that should cause the traffic lights
in the other direction to turn yellow.
We get the next event, both the traffic
lights should swap, right? Yellow to
red, red to green. And all of the walk
lights should swap, right? From blinking
to, you know, stop and from stop to go.
>> Right.
>> Right. So it's a single event that
happened at some specific time, but
because the machine is in a particular
state
where those different things are
parallel parts of that same state chart,
they might all trigger simultaneously
from that one event. What was the
question?
>> Um I had to uh so you're saying like in
parallel states like when there are
multiple active states and you send an
event, it's going to be delivered to
each state.
that. Yeah. And and that's where the
rules for what transitions fire come in
because it's not as simple as most
people think. When you fire an event, uh
you actually have rules around what
transitions are enabled, what
transitions are in conflict and
therefore then what transitions run.
Um so yes, more than one transition uh
uh can be active for a given event.
>> Okay. And um so um another trans
transitions do they always point inward
or can it sort of uh points to let's say
a parent or like maybe an uncle state
like maybe a sibling of the parent
state?
>> A a transition can point to anything
that has an ID.
>> Uh okay. And uh let's say it points to
outside maybe a sibling of the parallel
states and let's say another event
causes that state to then like is that
possible cuz like it's exiting the
parallel domain wherein not like you
know not
>> well we'll talk about event processing
here in a minute. I am going to get to
all the semantics here because this this
is part of my my goal is to is to teach
you what's going to happen.
But first I have to teach you what
parallel states are and that they run in
parallel right the regions run in
parallel so you understand the
terminology. So for here let's let's
kind of keep it to just definition and
we'll talk about execution semantics in
a minute.
>> Okay.
uh transitions can have more than one
target
because of parallel,
right? Because more than one thing can
be active at the same time in in these
child states. If I've got some
transition and I've got some particular
event that should cause multiple areas
of a parallel system to change, I can
say that this particular transition
should cause both the left ready and
right ready to become active.
So target can actually be a vector. It
can be a single keyword most the time
right when you don't have parallel
regions. But if you have parallel
regions, it's possible that you might
want to say what happens to multiple
parts.
You don't have to specify all of them,
right? You could just have left ready
and it would just move this one and this
one would stay wherever it was. Um, but
you can list multiple if you need to.
>> What will happen if we do a vector but
it's not a parallel, there are not
parallel children. to dig this compound
states.
>> That should be a state chart compile
error. Like it it shouldn't. If my
validations are right, it shouldn't
validate.
>> Okay.
>> But I'm not positive I have that
validation in there. I'm pretty sure the
processor would crash though if you did
that. Not positive. Um I I can't I can't
claim to have fully tested that edge
case.
>> Don't do it. uh it's not going to work
right
but yeah
>> okay um so discussion question in your
in in in our codebase uh can we think of
a couple of concerns that are currently
modeled as compound stains but are
actually independent
and would parallel regions simply the
chart claude wrote this I have no idea
what the answer is so
brainstorm with me
modeled as composting
>> for those who are most familiar with the
state charts and stuff.
>> Yeah.
>> Yeah. Let's see what Let's see what it
thinks the answer is.
>> It's just a generic question. It has a
question, but it doesn't mean in our
codebase. It just means in general.
>> Um,
right. So, if two concerns never
interact via transitions or respond to
different events, then you're going to
be using parallel.
uh
they do need to coordinate like only
allow X when Y is in state Z, right?
Then that's the natural nesting uh of
compound states.
Um
parallel is useful for things like this,
right? Am I logged in? Right? That's a
nice parallel region uh of of say a top
level system chart. In fact, I think
we're modeling it that way in Brazil,
aren't we, Gabo?
Have we gotten to that yet?
logged in, not logged in, right? Uh you
you could do that as compound, right?
And and in fact, you might uh you might
do off as compound if you're trying to
restrict say which routing states you
can get to in logged in versus logged
out. Uh then that might be a a compound
state might be better, right? because
you could say these are the routes that
I'm able to get to when I'm in the
logged in state versus the logged out
state. Now here's the only substates I
can get to, right? Um network status is
one that might be good because that's
kind of orthogonal, right? Say you've
got a websocket and the websocket loses
its connection. You might update the
chart with right in a parallel region
that's tracking whether or not the the
websockets connected, that sort of
thing.
Um,
okay, let's not harp on that too much.
Okay, so let's talk about this enabled
transition concept because this is one
of the most important concepts uh to
understand that you may not already
understand.
Okay, so what makes a transition
enabled?
Um, so number one, the source state is
active, right? So a transition isn't
enabled unless the state it lives in,
right? because transitions are placed as
as children of state nodes are in the
configuration.
Note that definition though
this this isn't this isn't the source
state is a leaf and active. This is the
source state is active. It's just in the
configuration.
Right? So that automatically gets you
when you're in some atomic leaf state
all of your parents transitions are
active
and in parallel right you can have
multiple
every one of the parallel regions uh is
active along with all of the whichever
leaves and and you know anything in the
chain from there.
Um
>> now this is an important uh point in in
parallel uh each region independently
searches for transitions right so so you
you're you're gathering up the list of
all the active transitions
that that it's kind of what I already
said right it's in the current
configuration if it's in the
configuration it's transitions are
available for for enabling it doesn't
mean they're enabled It just means
they're available. So this is the first
step. Step one, find all of the the
transitions that live as immediate
children to states that are in the
configuration.
Fairly simple algorithm to be honest. If
you've got the state chart normalized,
you just look for them, right? What
states are in the configuration? Okay,
what transitions are in those? Next,
does the event descriptor match the
event that's coming in?
Okay, so remember our our our uh event
matching earlier. What what does it mean
for an event to match, right? So number
two, the event matches that includes
event lists. So if you didn't put an
event on the transition, then condition
two, you're good, right? So one and two,
right? So now we have the list of
transitions that are in states that are
active that also match the incoming
events name.
Three, the guard is true, right? So if
there is a cond, if there's not a con,
then it's, you know, obviously true. But
if there is a cond, then we run it and
see if it's true,
right? So if all three of those are
enable, if all three of those are true,
then a transition is enabled,
right? So all three must be satisfied.
That doesn't mean they're going to fire
yet. We have another step, but this is
step one. Step one is pick all the
transitions that are available.
right? That that that that seem like
they match what we're trying to do.
Okay.
Then
for each active atomic state, so atomic
state in the configuration, right? So we
start this is this is where you get sort
of a bubbling behavior. So we start as
deep as we can go,
right? So we look through the current
configuration and we find the leaves,
the things that are just leaves.
If the transitions are on the atomic
state itself,
then we're going to select those in
document order. So in other words,
they're all going to fire, but they're
going to fire in the order they they
exist in the document, top down as you
would read it, not nested order, not
depth first or some weird thing like
that. Literally, if you're reading it
left to right, top to bottom, when you
reach it, if you're first, you're first,
right?
>> If and only if
none match on a particular stomach
state, then walk up to the parent and
see if it has transitions.
Keep doing that until a match is found.
Right? The first match wins for a given
atomic state. After
you've processed all the atomic states,
then remove conflicting transitions.
Right? So, we're not quite done yet. We
have to talk about what a conflicting
transition.
So, start with all the leaves.
If something matches on that leaf,
that's that's when you selected. You
stop looking. If there's nothing on that
leaf that matches, look in the parent.
If nothing matches there, look in its
parent. Nothing matches there, look in
its parent. If nothing matches, you're
done. there's that that thing isn't
going to have any sort of transition in
the list. Right?
>> So, what we've done here is we've built
a list of trans transitions that are
enabled. Now, note that for the most
part, uh if it's just a compound chart,
this is where it simplifies. If it's
just a compound chart with no parallel,
there is only one active leaf.
And so, you can sort of think of it as
bubbling, right? Did that leaf have a
transition? Did the parent have a
transition? Did that parent have a
transition? Right? It's pretty simple.
But as soon as there are parallel
things, then multiple atomic states can
be active. And that's where you get this
more than one thing can happen at a
time.
Okay.
Document order first match wins. We
already talked about that. That's
literally reading top to bottom. So in
this one, I guess we've sent an error
validation event. And what what
configuration are we in? Did it tell us?
>> I guess.
>> Oh, I guess there's just Yeah, there's
only one state. Yeah. Yeah. Okay. So,
we're looking at these. We sent an error
validation.
Uh
tries T3 first if guards falls to T4.
Then error.Validation.
Yeah, that would be T1. Yeah, it's in
document order. But in terms of the
algorithm, this matches and this
matches. Uh this does not match and this
does not match because the events don't
match. But there are two things that
match. But because the general catchall
is second, the list of two things that
match, uh T1 gets picked because in
document order that's the first one
found.
So this is how you can get kind of an if
else sort of thing. I'll catch specific
errors this way. and then catch the rest
of them this other question.
>> Uh I got confused. Um so the event send
is error.validation.
>> Yep.
>> But why does D2 matches if it's just
better? I thought it was the other way
around. If I send error, I'll catch
error. And error.
>> Okay.
Oh, the transition saying it matches
error means it matches anything whose
first token is error and error
validation does match that.
Right? So remember the first step is
>> figure out which ones are are available.
So I'm in some single state. I got an
error validation. This one and this one
both match on the event matching rule.
>> Right. That makes sense.
Uh
but document order this one's first.
It's the one that that
uh we we do right it's the one it's it's
right we've selected two
>> and then right we we have to do uh
conflict resolution. So this is right
this is the basic con conflict
resolution is all right for a given set
of transitions at a particular level the
first one is the one that wins.
If we send a save so this is the second
example. If we send a save event both of
these match on event
this one has a condition. So if the
condition is true this one's the one
that's going to go. If the condition is
false this one has no condition. This
one will go.
Makes sense.
>> Okay. Question.
>> Yeah. Yeah. So, basically the the
tokenizer works in a way where like
sorry
uh if it were uh like let's say we were
sending the event error only.
>> Yep.
>> And it would would only match T2.
>> Okay. So, it's like it's kind of like
the tokenization works on the event
itself and uh can match the transitions
like any transition that has um any of
the tokens from the event.
in the order that they Yeah. Yeah.
Exactly. They both get tokenized. You
tokenize both of them and then you're
looking for subpath matching, right?
>> Yeah.
>> Um
but only in one direction, right? So the
the you and it's meant for this fall
through behavior. It's meant for exactly
this case. I have something specific to
say about this specific one and I just
want to catch the rest of them some
other way.
Right? So, it's sort of like try catch,
right? Where you got you got the
inheritance hierarchy, right? Catch
exception info and then catch throwable,
right?
>> Yeah.
>> I've got something to do for exception
info and app everything else. Screw it,
right? I'll bail.
>> That's cool. That's because I had that
like I was that question was in the back
of the mind ever since you talked about
the tokenization. I was wondering how
that works here. So, I'm glad you
>> Yeah, that's exactly what it's for.
>> Nice.
>> Okay.
Um,
is there anything extra here to say
conditions on guards? There is a special
guard that's in the I think it's in the
elements name space called in. It
returns a lambda
that just checks to see if if the state
chart itself its configuration has this
state in it.
I
>> I could have sworn some saw something
else like a G or something somewhere or
an N. I think just a capital N
>> is there more keywords more things like
>> that's the only that's the only
>> there's ah there's some convenience
functions
uh you can say on
right and all this is is a function that
returns the same thing as transition but
it's just it's got the idea that well
the only thing you wanted to say was
event and target so you just put the
event name first and the target name
second and it'll it'll write it's just a
short hand.
>> Uh what else is there? There's a bunch
of them. There's a choice. Uh this emits
uh uh a sequence of transitions,
right? Um they're just convenience.
Uh they they aren't new kinds of nodes
then they're not in the standard.
They're just in in my opinion cleaner
ways of of
writing the chart. So what choice does
choice lets you specify
and I think a condition. So you you put
an expression here
uh and then a target
and then an expression
and a target
um etc. Sort of like a cond. It has
essentially the same basic structure.
I'm sorry, as a CA sort of like a case
or a cond, right? Um, and what this
emits is a sequence of transitions using
these rules, right? It puts con it puts
the same event.
Uh, what's the full Nico? What's give me
help me out here. So, the choice node
has an ID,
>> right? So this emits
>> has an
expression.
>> It emits a state.
>> Yeah, this emits a state that has a
transition
that is eventless
for every one of these cons.
And then I think there's a final
something like that or else. Yeah, you
say else basically.
>> Yeah. Um,
and this just expands
to a state with that many transitions on
it. It's just a shortand
>> one of the one of the in my opinion one
of the cool things cooler things that I
did in the state chart definition
system. It's just a data structure
but a uh this the top level thing that
interprets the chart into a normalized
data structure tolerates a node being a
map or a sequence of maps. So you can
write a function that emits
uh a sequence of nodes and it'll it'll
automatically uh splice them into the
data structure correctly
so that you can create these convenience
functions for making your state chart
cleaner
which is how that routing system.
Remember when we were looking at the
routing system, there was that uh
um
that thing that was emitting the
transitions
invokes
direct
transitions.
Right? This is a vector of transition
elements with event names and target
names from all the direct targets in the
routing system and then that's just
embedded in a vector down here.
Uh right there's a concat of an on entry
this transition and then these
transitions etc etc. This just splices a
state into the state chart that has
these children and so it makes it easy
to to make customized nodes for the
chart that aren't anything other than
states and transitions and and such.
Question
>> um yeah so I didn't quite get what you
said initially regarding this. Are you
saying like currently the state charts
library does the splicing?
>> Yeah. Yeah, it does it for you. So if
you go looking for the the on
Uh here this is just an apply of
transition with event target and then
the children that's it.
>> Okay. And
>> top level or is it only like top level
splicing that it does?
>> It recursively walks the data structure.
>> Oh okay.
>> Right. So so yeah you can you can do
yeah you can do sequence embedding in in
the places where it makes sense to do
sequence embedding like right here.
Right. I'm making a state and then I can
just drop a sequence of transitions
here,
>> right? And we're fine.
>> Okay. And uh the choice is it like cuz I
saw you wrote expressions and not
events. Uh is it like it matches on any
events for the choice the example? Yeah,
the point the point is what you're
trying to do is is you've got a
transition that targets this node
and and it's a decision node. It's not
meant to be stayed in. You don't stay in
this state. You transition to it and
then it fans you out to someplace else.
>> So any event is
>> Oh, all right. All right. So it doesn't
even wait for an event. As soon as it
transition here,
>> it transitions somewhere else. Yep.
>> Okay.
>> Yeah, because these are all event. So as
soon as you enter this state so this
outputs this as soon as you enter this
state it runs the eventless transitions
in it and right and there's a final
transition that's your else node that
will take you there. The only way it'll
sit in this choice node is if you didn't
have an else but that's not really what
you use the choice node for. use the
choice choice node for exactly this idea
of
um an event has happened but now I need
to make a decision whi where do I want
to go and writing it like this is not
very clear like to the reader of the
state chart you're like uh okay it's a
state right it takes you a few minutes
to figure out that this is just trying
to make a choice and so I made a choice
helper so then it's just really clear oh
I'm trying to make a choice I go here
and that makes me go somewhere else
Yeah. And I get transitions without an
event as sort of like on entry scripts.
>> They're not on entry. Uh um they they
fire whenever an event is firing. Um
>> as you mentioned, the choice is done
immediately you enter the state.
>> Help me out here, Nico.
uh
>> like I'm trying to understand that like
when you enter the node ID
state is going to do the condition is
going to go to that the question is the
on entry
>> no he's right he's right I've said this
I've said this slightly wrong the choice
node is a node you sit on is that true
>> we usually use it like with a current
state but it's just like the initial
>> like like in the subscription state
chart uh we use the choice node uh to
figure out uh uh where to go after some
event has happened like for example a
payment is received if I receive a
payment I go to a choice node and the
choice node checks to see if that fully
paid their account in which case they go
to the paid state or didn't satisfy
their balance in which case they go back
to the unpaid state right they still owe
us money that sort of thing So yes uh
the execution of this choice node
because it has eventless transitions
uh it will transition immediately upon
uh upon entry.
>> Okay.
>> On entry itself is meant to run
executable content.
>> Right? Executable content could raise an
event that takes you somewhere,
but executable content can't target you
somewhere.
>> Yeah.
>> Right. So, a script node, an on- entry
node couldn't move you somewhere else. A
trans an eventless transition can.
>> It could if there's an event, right? If
it calls an event.
>> Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. But that's that's
that's that's an event. That's not a
that's not a the state just became
active
>> uh kind of thing.
>> Yeah.
>> Yeah. So this is sort of a special case
that's designed into them for this exact
there used to be if you look at the
prior version of the state chart
algorithm there used to be a node like
this and they realized oh well if we
have eventless transitions you can model
that with state and transition we don't
need that extra thing and so they
eliminated it. So in older versions of
state charts, this was a formal thing.
And in the new version of state charts,
it's it's a thing they realized you
could do with sort of like sort of like
the problems we've been having with with
the RAD modeling, right? Where you do
something uh specialized when in fact
the generic already could handle the
case.
Uh so um two more questions like if you
don't want these transitions to be
eventless so you you need to add an
event uh event option and you know
>> in which case you wouldn't use the
choice node right the choice node is is
just meant to make it obvious that
you're using eventless transitions to
get this specialized behavior that's
very useful. That's why I made a
convenience. So why this name space is
called convenience is there are things
in here that just make it right like
send after
uh there's a send node
but if you use the send node it
schedules an event that is going to come
to you no matter what even if you leave
the state you're in most people what
they actually want is a send that
happens but only if I'm stuck in the
state right um if I've left the state
then I should cancel so this send after
is a convenience that emits an on entry
and an on exit that both schedules the
event and will cancel it if you exit the
state.
H
yeah, there's there's all sorts of
there's also convenience macros that
help with
>> uh diagramming like there's a choice
macro and what it adds in is uh uh sorry
what it adds in is uh a stringified
version of the condition in this prop of
the transition node so that drawing
tools can draw this label on the line.
So if you've if you said like you know
paid question mark as your expression
then the diagram condition would be the
string paid question mark and the
diagram could show paid question mark on
the line as its condition
right because it's a macro so it can
actually you know pull your source code
in as the format.
>> Yeah. Um I have one more question just
establish the rules for the eventless
transition. Mh.
>> So, um, if the first transition has an
event option and then the others do not,
like are they still eventless transition
or
>> they're still enabled?
>> They're still enabled. So, so let's go
back to the enabled rules. Um,
uh, so transitions are enabled uh,
right? For if the source state, right,
in this case, the source state is is the
this choice node. the state that's a
choice node um is in the current
configuration there is no event so of
course the event matches
right because the event is optional
and then cond guard is the only
protector there so the only thing that
keeps the transition from happening
would be a conditional guard or an event
so by putting an event on there because
an event isn't there
right well actually there is an active
event it's the event that just fired
that took you to the state from the
other transition.
>> Right.
>> Right. So actually that that event is
still technically the quote active event
and the state chart will continue
evaluating transitions until it doesn't
find any enabled. There's an internal
loop.
>> Okay. I thought it only does one
iteration then maybe.
>> No. Okay. We're getting that. until it's
sort of like stable state. No.
>> Yep. Until you reach a stable state
where there's no transitions that can be
taken. That's exactly what happens. Yes.
>> Yeah. So, so yeah, you can have very
complex sequenced
uh uh things happen on a single event.
>> Yeah. Um I'm just thinking like I don't
know cuz like I I I know that like state
machines initially were to simplify some
of those choice and condition complexity
and uh state charts. I don't know when
when you add in the parallel and all
these trans transitions seem complex.
>> So there's there's two I mean this is an
interesting if you go read the Herell
paper on state charts finite state
machines have been around for quite a
while. The problem you have with finite
state machines is a state explosion
problem. In order to model the the
actual behavior of complex systems in a
state chart, you get an exponential
explosion of the number of states you
have to have
to to sort of encompass the behavior of
the system. And what Herell realized was
that very often these these state
machines the state explosion people were
naming things that their individual
states states like checkout underscore
uh you know substate underscore substate
like they were making these big long
names for the state to stand for the you
know um my power is on on the boom box
and the cassette deck is paused.
Right? And by by making them
hierarchical, you solve that state
explosion problem. You get a much
smaller set of states that can model the
system. But then what he went on to try
to define was okay and he was working at
the time I think with uh airline
software like airplane software like
this is back when there were you know uh
uh trying to figure out how to write
systems that were critical right
software that that ran things like
airplanes where people's lives are at
stake and make it very clear how things
worked. And so he wanted to be able to
visualize
uh the the the software system.
And so what what he was trying to design
was kind of a feature complete system
that could represent what was needed to
model these complex systems as simply as
possible.
And that's what I love about them,
right? You can you can model extremely
complex systems in a tight com, right?
One of the things that we're constantly
working with in software design is
crosscutting concerns.
Uh being able to divide and conquer,
right? Break our program up into pieces
of logic, expressions, things like that.
But then composition, we need to compose
systems in a way where we can understand
them.
So for example like our um our login
page into Tao when you log into our
system uh you're running a state chart
that's actually very big and quite
complicated. It's got everything from
password reset onboarding
uh uh uh sign up
uh conditions around sign up handling uh
social login like Google initializing
the application preloading the
application config making sure all that
happens in order
uh it's actually the use case that I
ported state charts for because state
machines weren't good enough um and I
knew state charts were that that was the
initial use case. I think actually the
initial use case was subscriptions on
our system, but I realized the the login
startup it was constantly breaking. The
logic was spread all over the place.
There were mutations firing. The
ordering was all screwed up. There was
asynchrony you couldn't follow. It was a
mess.
But the complexity of the actual system
was high. The it wasn't incidental. The
incidental complexity was the fact that
we didn't have a way to compose the
system cleanly in a way you could reason
about.
But the real complexity of the problem
was actually quite high.
>> Right.
>> So, so you the question is
uh what's the minimally complex thing
you can build that will let you organize
a truly complex system
uh but isn't missing pieces that don't
let you model a part of it.
And that's what's beautiful about state
charts from my perspective, right? is
yes they've got some complexity to them
but that complexity is there to to
actually address
uh real problems and if you look at the
sequence of standards you can see
Herell's first proposal got simplified
by him that got turned into W3C spec
that got simplified in one or two
iterations like they actually were
removing things it's like what's the
minimum number of things we can have in
here and still be able to do all the
things you might need to do in a
Uh and the fact that you can get that
down to state transition
uh on entry on exit right parallel like
like a handful of of nodes in a chart
that can then be shown visually. I I
think that's beautiful.
>> Yeah, I think I agree. 25 minutes ago, I
literally asked Chat GBT like if
airlines use this kind of stuff, like
big ainers, and it said it does.
>> Yeah.
>> And like also like industrial system
because when you when you go into like
an enormous if you look at the cockpit,
>> I I I can't imagine how like what it
would take to code all of that stuff
that goes on other than, you know,
something like this because you would
just have conditionals everywhere and it
would make sense.
>> Oh, it's a mess. And how would you test
it? How would you debug it? Like it's
just Yeah. It would be a complete
nightmare.
>> Yeah. Like you you could just easily get
the airplane into like some invalid
states based on you know without
something like this I think. So
>> yeah and this and this gives you
something where you know you really can
you can test the hell out of this right
you can you can write tests that you
know plug in these these expressions as
as mocks and say okay when this
particular condition is true and this
happens we do this. All right when this
part right and then test the expression.
All right, does this detect it right?
Does the signal what if the sensor is
down? Blah blah blah blah, right? Um, so
you can actually do exhaustive error
analysis. Uh, and you've got these
conditions that can be catchalls or the
these events that can be catchalls,
right? Like a transition, a transition,
sorry, an eventless
transition with a condition, right?
Fires all the time, right? anytime
there's there's processing and its state
is active. Um,
uh, an event, the wild carding with
tokenization gives you a way to catch
things that you didn't expect,
uh, or need a catch all for, that sort
of thing. It's actually pretty pretty
beautiful, I think.
Um,
and it's why I've been pushing, you
know, we we need to be using these more
and more. Uh, to the point
>> Yeah. to the point in Brazil where it's
like, yeah, the entire system can just
be this. It's just state charts. We
don't need anything else.
It's kind of funny that these didn't
catch on more to be honest.
>> I I that's why I was just looking at the
stars on your library. I'm like 116 that
seems kind of like low especially for
the closure community.
>> Yeah. No, it's it's
>> I I once went to read a paper because
there was there's there's been a
question for years. I forget when the
paper was written. It's a long time ago.
It's like why don't people why don't
software systems in production like
production software systems in the
industry tend to use state machines and
state charts. And it was a really good
argument. They're like, "Well, you know,
initially people think their system's
going to be fairly simple and it's
really fast and easy to just, you know,
not think about it and just write your
little expressions and cobble it
together." And by the time you realize
you need it, you have such a large
hairball that with a whole bunch of like
built-in things that you didn't think
about that are sort of like if you
change how they behave at all, you've
got a bug that you're afraid to touch
them. And so, you don't refactor them.
You don't you don't bring them in when
you realize you need them because it's
too hard.
I think it's people just don't know
about these things either. Even
statement like
>> Yeah.
>> A lot of people like will just write
literally nested if statements. Oh yeah.
For everything.
>> And then uh
>> and I've seen it. I've seen that with
people and they don't they don't want to
improve either. They don't
>> they don't see what they're doing as
garbage.
>> Yeah.
>> It's all over the place.
I I think the um there is a closure
state chart library the one I'd used um
previously and uh it's it doesn't have a
bunch of these kind of things like it's
not really this like it's more so event
driven you know you have your state and
like I don't know
>> it's sort of weird
>> yeah Lucy uh Wang I think it is
>> I don't remember the author I think it's
CJ state chart or something
>> yeah yeah she she wrote her library
about the same time I wrote mine And
actually, she had released hers just
before mine. And I was like, cuz I went
looking. I was like, I want state
charts. I just need them. And and I
looked at hers and I was like, no, this
doesn't do what it needs to do. It's
like loosely based on the spec and
>> doesn't let you plug anything in like
this. This is not going to not going to
work. And so that's and and then I found
that the W3C spec, this was really nice.
Uh,
this was this was super nice. Uh, I went
to read this and I was like, "All right,
I should implement what this says
because this is a standard. It's got all
the semantics. If I implement what this
says, it'll just be right." Uh, and uh
um I was looking through it and there's
an algorithm. It's like actually got a
pseudo code algorithm that's complete.
And so I wrote very if you look at the
implementation in here it's it's a very
imperative like Java like it follows
this as close as I could follow it. Um
the only thing I did to make to make it
um
more functional was I made it so that it
wasn't it wasn't a closed tight tight
loop. actually split this into you've
got a pure function that does the steps
on a in input state and then returns the
output state and of course side effects
happen as you go so it's not it's never
purely functional because state charts
can side effect um and so I had to break
this main event loop this was the
hardest part of it I had to break this
main event loop into two because it says
while running right no it's not while
running I might have 100 threads running
events So um so I had to break this loop
in kind of in the middle uh kind of
right here right get an external event.
This this is the break point of the
algorithm.
But other than that, the algorithm is is
you know line for line as close to even
reading identically to this as I could
make it so that you could easily sort of
debug it and and try to um like I I I
think I even named the functions. I may
have closurized them, but I think I even
named it like select eventless
transitions and exit interpreter, you
know, etc.
Okay,
ready to continue?
>> Yep.
>> Anybody Anybody
jumping up and down to go pee or
something? We could take a
five minute break.
Nope.
>> I don't have to pee, but I appreciate
it. 5 minute break.
>> Okay. Yeah, let's take a let's take a
quick break.
Back at back at the top of the hour.
All right. Is everybody back? You back
here.
>> All right. Continuing.
>> I don't know if I don't know if
everybody else
um
>> top of the hour is being recorded. All
right. Okay. So,
there are two event cues. This is really
important to understand. And so, this
this goes to Jeremy's question around
uh the the is just one event processed.
And the answer is no.
So, here's here's the actual loop
simplified at the bottom. And the basic
idea is you have internal events and
external events. So external events you
actually have an external event Q right?
So that's what that event Q if you
remember from the protocols that event Q
protocol uh is where you can put events
that might have some say time at which
they're supposed to fire
uh or they could just be immediate. The
way our event Q is modeled on the server
side into Tao is you always put a time
in there and the time can default to
now. Right? I want I would like this
event to go as soon as possible.
This right these delayed sends that you
can define in a state chart and and and
send manually things like subscription
expires in a month. Uh that that's one
of the primary uses for this external
event cue. But really it's anything
that's externally motivated. So the user
clicks a button uh some server response
arrives in a fulcro chart. Um another
chart sends an event uh to a chart. Uh
all those are done uh uh via the
external queue.
Internal events have to do with
processing the chart itself. So the
chart itself can have a raise element
and the raise element actually puts uh
this event on the internal Q. So there's
another Q here just like the external Q
there's an internal Q and it is a Q it
runs in order uh and so you could have a
raise which is an executable content on
uh an element. You could transition to
another element that does another raise
and that would put another event on the
internal Q. So the state chart itself
can cause any number of events to be
plopped onto this internal queue.
Uh when a child
state for example let's say a a region
in a parallel chart reaches a final node
that automatically internally fires a
done state and the ID of the state
event.
So that that goes on the internal queue.
Uh if you've done an invocation, which
is like running another start state
chart and that state chart finishes and
you're still in the invocation, you'll
get a done invoke and the ID of the
invocation event on the parent chart.
Uh, and then if your expression engine,
your your processing, not the processing
engine, but the part that runs your
expressions receives say an unexpected
exception, it'll automatically throw an
error execution event on this internal
queue. Okay, what was the question?
Somebody raised their hand. You're
muted. Jeremy,
>> that was me. I I was muted. Yeah, I I
want to better understand the done state
and done in uh invoke events. So, are
they like at the top level?
>> These are events. They're sent to the
entire chart. Go back to the enabled
transitions
>> and process.
>> Yeah, great.
>> Now, this is when um the done state like
when exactly
>> we'll get to this. I'm going to we're
going to cover this. Um
>> Okay.
>> Yeah. So these dun have to do with
elements or or portions of a chart or or
child charts in the case of invocation
uh finishing reaching an end state.
Um and we'll get to when when that is.
So your internal processing loop right
so back in the in the um example I was
showing you a little while ago in our
code uh into ta code right where we we
say you know get
where was it? Uh, synchronous
send synchronous event. There we go. Get
working memory process event. Process
event is what we're talking about right
now. We're processing an external event
that was just handed to us. Here's the
external event. Get working memory,
process event, write working memory,
write working memory. That's basically
the the thing. So this process event,
this is the thing that's running this
loop,
right? So this loop processes any
eventless transitions.
So if we're in here and there are
transitions that are eventless and
they're enabled, right? Their conditions
are true, they'll run.
Then while the internal Q
is not empty, right? So this guy has all
these events that that are on it for
whatever reason.
uh pop event, do the select transitions
to figure out which which ones are are
going and then you know execute them
basically, right? Figure out the
conflicts, figure out the executable
content, do all the stuff, right? And
this is a loop. So until this Q is
empty, it continues running the things
on the internal queue.
And so the the the entry that we're
saying, right, this kind of gets rolled
to the top actually, right?
um is we accept an external event,
select the transitions in micro step and
then do this while loop and then we're
done. So that's process that's where I
had to break this loop up. Remember I
was telling you a minute ago that that
that large processing loop I had to
break it into two pieces uh so that so
that it wouldn't be this tight loop that
that goes forever. So that's why this is
simplified. Uh the actual processing is
typically uh driven by an external event
that selects micro steps and then
processes transitions does a loop until
everything stabilizes and the internal Q
is empty then it returns then you can
hand it one more external event etc.
Right? So you do the the the external
event loop is external to this
algorithm.
Okay.
All right. So, internal versus external
transition types. This one's really
important. This this comes in handy um
but can also bite you if you don't know
it's there.
So, the rule is for a transition with a
type specifier on it. This is optional.
And this is what it looks like. You just
say type internal or external. The
default is external.
If the transition is external
and that transition fires,
then the source state in other words the
the state that this transition is
located in as an immediate child. The
source state will be exited. So onexit
handlers will happen and re-entered. And
so the on entry will handlers will run.
That's really important. If it's marked
internal
then the source state is not exited. So
you won't get an on exit and on entry.
Now this whole thing about source state
location is important. Let me let me see
this. This answers your question. So
hold your question for uh for this. So
if I've got a state P, right? um and
it's got a transition in it, right? The
source state of this transition is P. If
state A has a transition, the source
state of this transition is A.
Okay. So if
P transitions to self, so P
transitioning it to self would be this
transition. The source state is P and it
transitions to itself.
Then by default it's external and onexit
on entry handlers inside of this state
will fire. So this guy pointing to
itself which you can do I want to do
some executable content and then
re-enter myself will exit and enter.
If you put transition type internal on
that transition and you get this event
and the source state is P, it will not
run the entry and exit.
If you're in A, the source state is A.
So if I go from uh the source state is A
and I'm going to B, then P's exit and
entry won't happen. Right? So so moving
from A to B inside of here, even if it's
an external transition
because the source of the transition is
A, A is the one that would have its exit
entry called, not P's.
So that's that's kind of the important
distinction. We do use this. We have
state charts where the transition is
explicitly marked internal to prevent
onexit on entry from firing. And I think
we even have some declared explicitly
external even though that's the default
just to make it very clear that we're
we're intending for the entry and exit
handlers to happen. Okay. So now what's
the question?
Um I was going to ask whether like um
all transitions can be triggered
externally and internally or is it
possible to limit a transition to only
internal or external transitions?
>> No no no no this has nothing to do with
that.
>> This has nothing to do with the event
type.
>> Oh just
>> this is this is a marker on the
transition to indicate how the
transition behaves with respect to its
parent its source state. That's it.
Events being external or internal have
to do with whether they came from the
internal queue or the external
>> queue,
>> right? Totally different concept.
Unfortunate overloading of words,
>> right? So, this isn't I respond to an
external event or I respond to an
internal event. Completely orthogonal.
So, great question. I'm glad you brought
it up. Uh uh same word, unrelated.
Okay. So
remember I talked about conflict
resolution earlier.
Uh
one element of conflict resolution is
just the document order. Right. I've got
multiple transitions that enable and if
right only one from an atomic state of
those transitions uh that that matches
uh will be taken in document order.
Um if there's an explicit match um for
parallel regions uh you've got another
possible conflict
uh when their exit sets overlap right
and when we say exit sets we're exiting
the parallel parent
right so so for example this state has a
transition that would stay inside
right it's going to maybe some you know
target that's inside of panel A
somewhere they haven't shown it here and
panel B has an event same event which
targets something outside of the
parallel region. Well, this is a
conflict. One's trying to completely
stop all the states in the parallel
system and the other is trying to do
something in the parallel system.
Right? So that's a different kind of
conflict.
So if you have this kind of conflict
then the transition that
uh uh uh
the
deeper source wins and if that's a tie
document order breaks the tie.
So in this case the panel A wins
um not because it's deeper but because
it's first
right so both C reset they conflict
because one wants to exit the parallel
region and the other doesn't and to
resolve the conflict uh either the
deeper source so if this transition was
nested three levels down it would win
uh even if it was down here in in panel
B. So if it was deeper in the document,
it would win. Otherwise, document order
wins.
>> Follow.
>> What happens to the other transition
that does not win?
>> This one just doesn't get selected,
right? Because this transition would
force the whole thing out of the
parallel region, which would cause the
entire parallel thing to to be done.
Right? It wouldn't the parallel state
wouldn't even be active anymore.
Dashboard wouldn't be in your
configuration. Panel A wouldn't be
right. None of this stuff would be in
your configuration if this one won.
And that's what creates the conflict is
this one's trying to do something within
the parallel state and this one's trying
to exit the parallel state. That's the
conflict.
>> Yeah, I understand that. I imagine
parallel um uh the parallel regions are
sort of spawning you know parallel
actors. So then the actor that was on
panel B like what what happens to it?
Does it like
>> there's no such thing as actors here? I
don't know what you mean by actors.
There's just states
there's side effects and there's states
that's that's what you have.
But but I guess like the final
configuration will be just it stays on
panel B.
>> Yeah, it would stay in panel B.
>> Panel A in it.
>> Yep.
>> Yep. And that So you'd have dashboard
panel A, panel A and it if that's some
child, we assume and panel B.
>> I don't know if that was your question,
Jenny.
And if if the if the targets weren't
here in any kind of conflict, like let's
say there was executable content and
that's all that was here. They just each
had their own script element. They would
both run
because there's no conflict then.
So with no conflict, all of the
parallels, they're all enabled. They all
run with a conflict. One's trying to
exit the parallel region, the other
isn't. The deeper one wins. And if that
doesn't
if they're tied then document order ones
that's it. There's nothing else to it.
>> So a conflict is when it says there like
when one is target is outside and the
other one is inside.
>> Yep.
>> And that's that's unusual. I mean I mean
>> if Oh that's a great great question. If
both was the question
>> if both leave if both are leaving the
parallel.
Uh
that's an interesting question. I don't
know.
So you're saying if both said if both
said something we're we're leaving.
>> Yeah. Let's say one.
Yeah. Log in.
>> I I'm I'm I'm guessing that that's still
a con conflict, but the document order
wins.
Okay,
>> the semantics are really solidly defined
by that algorithm. It'll behave the
same. It's not going to behave
erratically.
Um, and document order, I can just tell
you in the spec, document order is like
the king. If I can't decide what to do
and there's a question of what to do,
document order. Like that's that's what
and and since this can't possibly
uh do both if if logged out and logged
in are two different states in a
compound section of the chart they both
can't be active at the same time. So
that would be I guess that would be
another conflict. Um but but yeah I
didn't write all these slides so I'm I
didn't think about that that case and so
I'm guessing I don't know for sure.
Okay.
>> It it would be a silly chart to write.
So I would hope that you wouldn't write
it.
>> Yeah. I'm seeing that with all this
state library like you have a
like a like a ton of possibilities of
things to do or like if you want to
achieve something you have
>> a ton of ways of doing it. So
>> yep. So, so Tony, not pictured here is
like a a different state on the same
level as the parallel ID dashboard
called login,
>> right? Yeah. Yeah. That's that's like
we're we're we're the slide was right
getting too big. The idea here is you've
got a state down here.
>> Yeah. I was confused for a little bit
because I was listening to you talk and
>> Yeah, that's that's the idea. And then
and then inside the stays inside we have
we have some we have like a state within
this state.
>> Okay.
>> Exactly. That's that's the ID. Yep.
>> Yeah.
>> I guess you guys were just using your
imagination while I was confused.
>> Crazy.
>> Can there be a direct transition under
parallel?
>> A direct
like states.
>> I don't know what you mean.
>> Like uh the direct children of uh
parallel the parallel node
>> parallel is a state.
>> Yes. Okay.
>> It just has a Yes, you can do that. Yep.
You can have on entry, on exit,
transition. Yeah.
>> Okay.
>> Yep.
The the docu the documentation is really
good and clear on this. So if you if you
do the W3C state chart, you know, uh uh
document here and you just pick a node
uh like parallel, uh it tells you what
attributes it takes and then what
children it can have.
>> Okay, cool.
>> And I'm trying to figure like if there
is a transition like um
are all states still active?
I don't know for
>> it depends on what your transitions do.
That's a great question and that's a
that's coming up. That's actually a
really good question. We'll we'll we'll
do that soon.
Okay. Um
what if one region has no matching
transition and the search walks up to
the parallels parent? Okay. So, right,
we have this idea that there's a
transition up here that can catch a
particular event. Um and we say shut
down. And so we've got, right, these are
both active. There's nothing there. The
walks up, right? The algorithm says go
to the parent, go to the parent, go to
the parent, and then run the transition
in in question. Um, so there's no match,
no match, walks up the app, binds the
transition. Same for panel B. Both
select the same transition. Uh and the
result here is we end up exiting the
entire parallel
uh chart and we go to off.
Is that true?
>> Oh yeah. Yeah. Yeah. It would be it
would be true here. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah.
Because because parallel is a child of
this state, right? And so we're saying
that that there's a a sibling here. Uh
for some reason the font is coming out
the wrong color.
It didn't do a very good job of putting
other things in here. Right? So, if I
send an event and there's a transition
here in the parent of the parallel,
right? The the event is seen by these
states. But if it walks out of the
parallel region, finds a matching
transition that takes it somewhere else,
then the whole parallel like exits,
right? You're done. All the onexit
handlers will happen and all these all
these will stop. Um,
>> right.
>> And if it's only one is the same
conflict issue as the previous slide
slide
>> only one.
It's not a conflict then,
right? If I had a transition in here
for event shutdown
to run some executable content or
something, that's fine. It'll handle it.
It'll just stay in that state. The other
one will stay in its state. You're fine.
>> Yeah.
>> Right. The reason I had it generate this
slide, I remember when I made this two
weeks ago, so I remember now I I wanted
this slide to be there because of the
enabled transitions thing. walks to
parents. And what happens if you walk
out of parallel and hit a transition
and and right if you hit this
transition, that's the source state.
There's the target. You're no longer in
this guy. And if you're no longer in
that guy, you can't be in any of its
parallel sub regions.
>> It's kind of obvious when you think
about it, but it's it's one of those
things where it's like, oh, all right,
that that could be unexpected, right, if
I'm not paying attention.
So, I'm I'm a little bit confused like
how isn't this a conflict because one of
the states has a transition and the
other states has nothing to transition
to.
>> Ah, remember that. Oh, wait, wait, wait.
You're right. You're right. That is a
conflict. And this is the deepest, so it
would win,
>> right? Because this one's way more
shallow. So, this is the deepest
transition.
>> Um, I don't know. Like, okay. So
>> you're right. You're right. It's a
conflict because all states do evaluate
the event. This one would still walk to
here and enable that transition. This
one would walk to here and enable that.
Those would be the two enabled. They'd
be in conflict because this one causes
the parallel region to be exited,
right? And this one doesn't.
>> Yeah.
>> And therefore it would select the
deepest.
And and that makes sense, right? You'd
want the deepest rule to keep the
parallel region alive.
Okay,
>> go ahead Jeremy. I will ask something.
>> So like I'm still trying to wrap my head
around because I've always been thinking
about parallel state as parallel actors
>> but like it seems it's simply like okay
there are multiple active states and you
can run multiple transitions for that
state
>> and if there's a conflict you simply do
not run any transition for that. you
know the inferior the other states that
lost.
>> Yes.
>> Yeah. So be careful in in interpreting
parallel to mean like threads. There are
no threads here,
right? There's there's no threads.
There's there's an algorithm running the
chart and the and the algorithm is just
that loop. It's one thread. There's only
ever one thread. Unless you spawn
threads in your expressions, you could
do that. But the as far as the state
chart interpretation goes, there's only
one thread. And so when you say
parallel, all you're saying is these
things will be in the configuration in
parallel,
>> right?
>> That's set because think about it. The
the only thing that the state charts
actually tracking over time is the data
model which you use in your expressions
for things like guards and what set of
states are active. That's it. That is
the complete data set of the entire
state chart system.
what state you're in.
So when you fire an event, all the state
chart algorithm is trying to do is
decide which executable content to run
and which states to end up in.
>> That's it. That's all it's trying to do.
It's actually way simpler than I think
you're making it in your head.
>> Yeah.
>> Yeah, I think I I get it now.
>> Okay.
>> All right. Uh mixed match. What if we
inside has to walk up the parent? We
just did that, right? Uh stays inside
exits conflict panel a sources deeper.
Yeah. So we figured that out on our own.
Um ah now here's the fun.
>> I have a question. Yeah. On the the one
before like what if the transition
the pattern transition has a a script is
going to be run just one?
If you had
>> only enabled transitions run.
>> Yeah.
>> If there if you had this case this guy's
a conflict and it would be thrown out.
So his executable content would run
>> because let's say you don't have the one
inside as it was at the beginning.
>> Oh well then there's no conflict. You
exit the parallel state and yes the
executable content here would run as
would things like on exit.
>> H the impacts only run once. My question
was like there are like two states and
>> ah no no no yes it's it the transition
is what enabled is enabled it's not
related to the states the states are
exited so if they have onexit handlers
those will run these will all run
right
>> okay
>> so you you can have a whole bunch of
crap happen as you exit but that's
executable content on the states the
transition is a transition.
>> Okay.
>> Yeah.
>> Got it.
>> So as you as you traverse this edge, you
run its executable content. Now it could
target a different set uh of parallel
states in a different parallel region
and all of their on entry handlers could
run, right?
>> Yes. So you could have three on exits
happen and then the transition happens
and then two on entries happen, right?
There's a whole bunch of whole bunch of
stuff that can happen.
This this executable content could
include arrays
uh that adds another event to the uh
internal event queue that's then gonna
going to be right done after all of that
mess happens,
right?
I I didn't quite understand like um if
there are two active states and then
they exit the parallel does the on exit
run twice
>> no no no
>> once this so so these run in inverse
depth order uh panel panel let's see now
which way will go a little deepest in
document order so I think this one on
exit will run it's well defined this one
will run then this one will
Um I think then the transition
executable content runs
>> uh then as you're entering the states
then you'll get the executable content
of those states in document order etc.
>> I like it.
>> Yeah, you do not get arbitrary execution
order and you don't get duplicates.
Right. This this onexit isn't run once
for each of these children.
It's exiting this guy. Right.
>> Yeah.
So you won't get duplicate runs and you
won't get random order. You'll get a
very well- definfined order.
>> Yeah.
>> And I'm pretty sure if I remember right,
I'm pretty sure the entry order is um
document order outer in
and exits are kind of the opposite. It's
still document order but inner out,
right? because you're it's as if you're
exiting the innermost states first and
then exiting their parents and then
exiting their parents, etc.
>> Okay.
>> Yeah.
>> Sorry, I was allowing Jeremy to talk
about actors, so I had a question this
entire time.
>> Okay,
>> go back one.
Just go back to that example that we we
were looking at.
>> This one?
>> Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. This one.
So, so basically like we were before you
had uh this like the second thing the
transition event shutdown within the
dashboard
>> uh let's say right
>> uh if if the event shutdown arrives
that would would that only uh trigger
the the within the parallel state
dashboard if dashboard was in the
configuration.
>> Correct. Correct. The dashboard has to
be active for for any of these states to
be active for them to be looking for
active transitions,
>> right? And so if dashboard is in the
configuration
>> and and and
>> would would app be as well like
implicitly because
>> app is in app is definitely in the
configuration.
>> Okay. Okay. So then it then walks right
up and then hits the that shut down.
>> So you're saying if there's a transition
here
>> Yeah. Yeah.
>> Yeah. And then I'll go to that target.
And then if uh if dashboard was not in
the configuration, it would just go
straight to app and look for that
transition for shutdown.
>> Well, it depends on what these other
things have in them, but yes, it it
right if that's if that's the only place
that shutdown's defined and whatever
you're in at whatever level, you'll end
up walking up to it.
>> Yeah. And that's just that again that
just goes that's why this was so early
in the talk. What makes a transition
enabled?
>> Yeah.
>> Right. that you when you go to find
process and event you look for all
enabled transitions. You literally look
at the entire chart for these three
things
and then selection right is is this
sequence
and then conflict resolution is the
other bits that we've been talking
about.
So one minor thing we're talking about
like invocations about like calling
different state charts and then you have
like a rays
>> is that kind of like a similar thing
>> because a state chart calling a state
chart and then you have the rays going
to another state
>> and raise is always it just puts an
event on the internal queue which then
walks that this this loop we talked
about for the for those right you have
an internal event cube all raise does
stick something on that cube it's all it
does
invocations are whole different thing.
Not even not even two those yet.
>> Jeremy is stabbing his hand.
>> Okay.
>> Yeah. Yeah. Um I think we need to can we
go back to the other parallel screen?
Last one.
Uh okay. So now um if we are in the
parallel states and panel A and panel B
are active then an event causes panel B
to transition to panel A that means that
there's now only one active states and
you can never get two active state out
of that. Is that correct?
>> Like panel A and panel B are active.
>> I hear you. I don't know that that's a
valid state chart construction.
Um,
>> right. If you're if if you're wanting to
exit a child state of a parallel child
region, basically a state that's an
immediate child of a parallel element.
Uh, you use a final node within that
state.
Uh, you can transition out of the
parallel.
But your question of if I transition
from one parallel region to a different
parallel region, does that cause me to
exit?
>> Yeah. Is it sort of like one of them
exiting? Like let's say basically two uh
>> I I can't answer the question, Jeremy,
because I I've never considered trying
it because that's not really what
parallel is meant for. You're not meant
to treat them as compound sibling states
that can transition between each other.
Uh I don't know if the validation would
catch that and tell you it's an invalid
chart. Uh it may be a use case I didn't
think of in the validation. Uh and it
could be that it's valid technically
under the semantics of the standard and
I'm just not aware of what it should do.
See I can't tell you. I can't tell you
what it would do. You shouldn't do it
but I can't tell you what it would do
>> in general. We shouldn't like you know
design our stuff such that you know one
of the parallel states can you know
transition into another like you know
they can meet at the same we should
avoid that basically.
>> Okay.
>> Right. It's it's undefined in the
semantics of the construction like the
whole point of parallel is that all of
the siblings with who are immediate
children of the parallel are are all
active simultaneously.
Now, I'm about to talk about them
becoming inactive independently because
that can happen. That's actually
allowed. Um
uh but but I've never thought of trying
to do it by what you just suggested
>> because there's a formal way of doing
that, like leaving or exiting a one of
these child states, just one. There's a
way to do that that's official. Um what
you're suggesting to do is nonsensical
and shouldn't validate,
but I can't I I can't guarantee that it
won't.
>> Okay. And that's
>> right. So final is the node that we're
interested in. So So state charts in
general, like when you draw them, you've
got like a a node that's like your
initial entry point that takes you to
some initial state, which can have
substates, right? And you can transition
amongst these substates or you can
transition to some other state which
might have substates and all of this
could of course live in some bigger
compound state etc.
Um a state chart can finish right and
that's usually modeled as like a
termination node that you can an event
can transition to that basically means
this state chart's done.
Um and when a state chart's done then
its session is cleaned up. you if you
try to send more events to it, it just
does nothing. It's like dead. Um, right?
You're done with that process. State
charts don't have to have a final state,
right? Some state charts like our
subscriptions, they just run forever.
They're either paid or unpaid. They're
active or inactive. They just keep
going. They never end. U, but it is
possible for a state chart to end. And
it's also possible for a parallel sub
region of a uh of a state chart to have
a final node. This kind of final node is
a final node within the parallel region.
It doesn't terminate the entire chart.
So, so this would be a final node uh at
the very top right of the chart.
Actually, this final technically if I
had a compound state like that, there
could be another state over here. Um and
and this one reaching final doesn't
necessarily
exit the chart. particularly for example
if this was parallel that kind of thing
right so uh uh the final node doesn't
mean the state chart exits it means this
is the final node in some particular
region
of the chart
this is particularly important for
parallel regions because this is what
allows you to potentially exit right
have task A drop out of the
configuration
separate from task B. So it is possible
in this parallel region to see task A
and task B or just task A or just task B
if final has been reached.
Right? So before I before I take the
question, uh the basic idea here is um
uh you do get an event when this
happens. When you enter a final state of
some region, that's where you get the
done event that we talked about earlier
in the internal event queue. If you
reach this, you'll get a done. So you
could put a transition on here that
catches the quote done event and right
does something.
Um
uh
if all of the regions in this final have
exited, then you will have gotten a done
event for each one of the states.
Processing could technically still be
the the active state if there was no
transition out of it. It's just none of
its children will be in the
configuration.
>> Okay, what's the question?
>> Uh you literally just answered it. I
gave every
>> Yeah.
Yeah, let me let me finish the slide
before raising your hand. Um,
okay. So, that's the idea there. For
most of our use cases, it's it's rare
that you'll, you know, you'll do this
sort of thing. Typically, when you have
a parallel region, it's because you
want, you know, something to kind of run
forever and something else to kind of
run forever within your chart. That's
most of the use cases that we hit. But,
it's it's important to know that this is
a possibility just in case it comes up,
right? This is all about having the
tools in your toolbox.
Um, and so here's the the done state
events.
Um, so complete chart exit requires a
top level final like this, right? So
this top level final will cause the
entire working memory and entire chart
to be garbage collected. If you've not
reached this top level final state, then
the the the chart's still technically
active. You can still send events to it.
uh it'll still try to react. Um
so you could have parallel going here
with a final and a final, right? And
when when these exit, so tasks, where we
at? So parallel tasks. Um oh yeah, I
forgot about this. Sorry, I I said one
thing wrong. If all of them exit, then
this top level state also exits and
sends a done event. So done state tasks
means the parallel region all of its
things have finished.
That won't exit the chart. But if you
add a transition for that particular
event that takes you to a top level
final, that will exit the whole chart.
>> Right? So when you reach this state, you
get a done state task A event, which
we're ignoring in this example. If you
reach here, you'll get a done state task
B event, which again we're ignoring in
this example. um and then both are final
then you'll get a done on the parallel
and then that lets you transition uh
some other way whatever it might be
>> I I guess it's impossible to have an
outside transition that caches the down
state of one of the regions because of
the conflict
that's like impossible right
>> uh no there's no conflict if there's no
transitions in for it then there's no
conflict.
I mean it depends on what the transition
does. If the transition tries to
transition it out of the chart and a
different one tries to keep it in, then
there's a conflict. No, none of the
rules have changed.
>> Yeah.
>> Right. You can put a handler for done
state task B or A anywhere in the
hierarchy
and it will be an enabled transition.
Whether or not it fires depends on
conflict resolution. So it depends on
what it does. If it catches the event
and just runs a log statement, it'll
run. It'll log,
right? But if it has a target and the
target causes a conflict, then it won't
run, right? Uh if there's an internal
one that that overrides it that stays
inside.
>> Yeah.
>> Okay.
Uh
ah this is a good point. I didn't
remember this. I'm glad this is here.
When one side of a parallel is final and
the other isn't, the final state is in
the configuration.
So this isn't this is right. Final is
just a state with an ID. If you don't
give it an ID, it'll generate one,
right? And if you generate one, then you
won't be able to catch its events and
you won't understand what that event,
what that state is in your
configuration.
Um
but the the finished until you're out of
that parallel state completely
um uh you'll have the the final state
ids in the configuration.
Okay,
we've had a lot of discussion so I think
I'm going to skip the discussion.
We got got a decent way to go still and
uh a lot to talk about. Uh and there are
exercises.
Okay. History
poof.
This is taking a lot longer than I
thought it would, but it's good. Good.
We're having lots of questions. I feel
like everyone's kind of getting a better
understanding.
All right. History nodes are about
remembering where you were in a compound
state that you've exited during the
session.
Um,
so example multi-step wizard. So let
let's say you take someone to a route
and they're walking through a multi-step
wizard and they get to step three and
they're like, "Oh crap, I need to go fix
my profile." And they go and fix
something in their profile which is a
different route. And they they're like,
"Oh, right, right. I need to finish
setting up my onboarding or whatever.
They come back to the wizard. It might
be nice to put them back in step three.
They've already finished one and two.
You can do that in two basic ways. Uh
way number one, which we do in the
subscription state chart intentionally,
is we don't use history.
uh we actually examine the state of the
system and try to figure out where
you're supposed to be through logic. We
do that so we can restart the state
chart and have it pick up where it left
off according to the database.
The reason for this is because we side
effect invoicing and payments,
right? So I don't want it to remember
that you're in a paid state if I have to
restart you. I want it to look to see if
your invoice got refunded, right? I want
to see that it puts you in the state
that actually matches the state of the
real world.
So,
history is meant to make the state chart
track where it was when you left a
compound state and then came back. Um,
but it's optional. You can add it in and
it's a special node you add. And that
history can be either deep or or or
shallow and we'll talk about what that
means, but that's that's kind of what
it's meant to be. It's actually
implemented in a very simple way. It's
just kind of memoizing
uh uh the substate you were in in a
state
uh so that if you go to the history
node, you'll reenter that saved memoized
thing.
Um
so
there's a type shallow and a type deep.
Type shallow only remembers
the top level siblings. So if this is
the state hierarchy, there's a wizard
state, a history node, a step two, one,
step two, and then within step two,
there's substates 2 A and 2B that are
nested as children.
Uh
then the history, if you exit the wizard
state, will only remember if you were in
step one or two. It will not remember 2
A or 2B.
So if you come back to the history node,
it'll restore say step two, but then
step two will always jump to 2A, which
is its default initial. It won't go to
2B, even if that's what you were on.
With deep, it remembers the entire
hierarchy of active states in the
configuration relative to wizard,
right? So So here, if you navigated away
and were on 2B and then came back, you'd
still be on 2B.
Uh there's no way to specify how deep
deep goes. It's just all of it, right? I
guess in their analysis and the papers
and specs and stuff, they decided that
they didn't need you to be able to
specify the depth you wanted. Um I'm not
sure why. I think possibly because you
can construct any uh limited depth with
a sequence of shallows. You could put a
shallow here and a shallow there and a
shallow and a shallow, right? That would
give you arbitrary depth, but for
convenience, typically you either want
one level shallow or all of it.
Question about the concept.
>> Yes, I think I was not paying attention,
but the history note has to be a sibling
note for the ones.
>> Yeah, I'm going to talk about the actual
coding of it here in a second. More more
concept of just shallow versus just deep
is all we're trying to do here.
>> Oh, no. Yes.
>> Okay. The way this actually looks and
this this is important. Uh you do put
the history node on the the the
kind of the immediate child of the state
whose history you're trying to record.
You specify the type deep or shallow.
Again, you can put history nodes on
children. So if you don't say deep, you
can sort of record right the partial
graph if you want by just nesting more
history nodes.
Now, here's the trick.
If you want history to trigger, then
your transition has to transition to the
history node,
not necessar not like some specific
substate,
right? The history node will only apply
if it's the node that gets transitioned
to.
That's that's the main trick, right? So,
this history node says if you transition
to me and I don't have history, I'll go
to step one. If I do have history, I'll
take you to whichever configuration I I
was in last time you were here.
But, but be very careful that you uh
when you target transitions into the
state where you want to restore history,
you shouldn't even target the top level
thing. the top level things initial will
target the history node. Um uh but
that's sort of like you're relying on
document order kinds of things. You're
much better off targeting the history
node explicitly when what you want to do
is restore history.
So that's that's my main point here is
you you should target wizard history not
wizard
if you're trying to invoke the history.
If you're trying to skip the history,
even if it's there, then target step
one. Like just target the thing you want
to go to. I want to start the wizard
over. Target step one.
>> Right? That gives you both
possibilities. You're not stuck with the
history that it recorded.
>> Okay.
And that's what this slide is about.
Okay.
invocations.
Anybody have any other questions about
history? I mean, it's just recording the
configuration. Um, and
on entry, on exit behaves like you're
entering or exiting the states, like all
that stuff works just as you'd expect
it.
The only trick is the transition that
you use.
Okay.
Ah. Oh. Oh. Oh. One more note. One more
note. If you if you target wizard, I
forgot history isn't technically a
state. And so this guy's initial will
default to this state. Period.
Because history isn't a state. It's a
marker indicating you want to record
history.
So that that's an important Yeah, that's
an important one. If you target wizard,
even this history is the first thing,
you won't get history. You have to
target the history.
I wonder then why wasn't history like an
option? So um
>> I don't know. I think because it wants
to be modeled in the diagram as a
special thing like when you're when
you're drawing a state chart uh and and
a node has history uh it's drawn as a
circle with h that transitions to a
particular node by default.
>> That's how it's drawn. And so I think
they wanted it to be a separate node
just so that you understand it gets its
own diagramming element.
>> Right.
>> Okay.
>> All right. Invocations.
Invocations are essentially state charts
you want to run from another state chart
that are controlled by the parent. Okay,
this is different than starting a state
chart that uh you just run arbitrarily
like I can start a thousand subscription
state charts. They aren't related in any
way, shape or form. They all run in
parallel, right?
uh technically in an expression of a
state chart I could spawn in our system
a new session with a new state chart
that's completely unrelated to the
parent.
Right? So this is different. Okay. So so
separate the idea of there's a way to
run a state chart. There is. There just
is. You can start it. You give it a
session ID. You give it the state chart
definition. It's running. Period. No
relation whatsoever. If you want to send
an event, you need to know its session
ID. Uh if it wants to send you events,
it needs to know your session ID.
There's no join point unless you invent
it.
Invocations have a joined point.
Um and control.
So an invocation is a node that can
invoke actually a state chart or
anything else you want to plug into the
system. You can actually create
invocation processors
uh that we we saw there's a protocol for
this. If you implement that protocol
with a 100 different things, then there
will be a 100 different kinds of things
that your state chart can control.
Here's the semantics though. An
invocation starts when its state is
entered.
So the state chart here would run when
this invocation is active. And if the
invocation state is exited, then the
child state chart is automatically
killed.
Now, it's it's actually sent a
termination event and allowed to process
that. So, it doesn't just get like, you
know, kill minus 9 sort of Unix style,
you're dead. You don't even get to know
it um for state charts. But I've got an
example in the repository that has a
future invocation where you can invoke
something that runs in the future and
when you leave the invocation, it calls
future cancel on it. It's just a way of
like having the state chart be able to
start a thread to do some processing and
then if you exit that state it it it
finishes the thread that sort of thing.
So, so invocation life cycle is
controlled by the state chart. So that's
nice, right? You can stop and start it
automatically without having to have an
on-end entry and on exit and all that
mess. uh it also has the ability to
automatically forward events from the
parent chart through to the child chart
as long as it's active or the child
invocation. Right? So that future if it
invents some sort of way of receiving
events from the event queue because the
protocol has a hey I send you I'm
sending you an event kind of thing then
then that thread could receive
instructions from the parent chart that
sort of thing. So it's a it's a
completely abstract generic interface
that we largely just use to run state
charts. And this is the default type of
an invocation is a state chart.
Um when state charts
uh
finish then you'll get a done.invoke
with the ID of the child.
These IDs are autogenerated in our
system and they're actually uh UU IDs I
think. So this is not a fun thing to get
explicitly but if you give the child an
ID then you'll get that specific
uh uh done event
questions on the basics here
>> um I'm trying to understand the uh
forwarding so like if there is no auto
forward
>> if there if there's no auto forward then
nothing really happens Right. Uh the as
long as you're in this state, you're in
that invocation, uh that invocation is
running. If you leave the parent, the
invocation ends. U that's it. If the
invocation terminates before you leave
its state, then you'll get this event to
tell you, yeah, that invocation's done.
Um so that you can like transition away
if if you were just waiting for the
invocation to to finish with autoforward
true. As long as this invocation is
active, any events received
uh by this state chart are forwarded to
the invoked state chart. So both your
parent state chart and the invocation
invoked state chart get that event. It's
just copied onto its event.
>> Yeah.
>> All right.
>> And okay. Okay. So there is no wait cuz
I was thinking like okay if the child
doesn't
match the event doesn't find any
transition then that's when the parent
gets it. Okay.
>> Oh no it goes to both. Yeah it goes to
both. So there's no transition since
this isn't a transition. Your transition
enabling rules still apply to the outer
chart.
>> Um
>> okay. Uh
although that's interesting
uh with the auto forward to be honest I
don't know what happens if you have a
more deeply nested atomic state
uh that has a transition that captures
that event.
I I my understanding is auto forward
just every event that happens on the
thing while it's active it just passes
along.
>> There's no filtering whatsoever.
And and I guess you can send external
events to that.
>> Absolutely. If you know the state charts
ID, yes, if you know the invocation's
ID, uh then then yes, you can use the
external event Q to send events. uh as
well.
Uh you can also and this should be oh
that should have been the next
oh there's a little bit more to
invocations and that's that the child
chart has the parents the invoking
parent session ID and it can send an
event to the parent from the child and
when you do that uh uh you can actually
have a node called finalize
that pre-process the event before this
before it's actually then processed by
the state chart algorithm.
uh it's a way of morphing it's it's an
adapter pattern. It's basically a way of
adapting things that are coming from a
child chart into your parent chart uh
before your parent chart does something
else with them.
>> Okay.
>> So there's birectional communication
mechanisms basically all you need to
know. You can look at the documentation
and tinker with it to to actually get it
to work.
So life cycle event forwarding child can
talk to parent. So they're connected.
Uh so imagine like in the routing system
we've got forms and reports and things
like that. If you make a report an
invocation then the report starts when
you enter the invocation but it's a
separate state chart that runs that
report. And when you leave that route
the invocation kills the state chart
that was running that report. So it's no
longer in your state. and
um that kind of thing.
>> So as an example of usage,
>> but you can have it such that the routes
like when you want to leave the route
sends it to the child invocation, the
child state chart and that determines
whether or not maybe the form is dirty
and
>> sure. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. That's
designed into the routing system though.
That's not just part of state charts,
right? That's the routing system. It's
actually kind of a complex mechanism,
right? because an invocation has to go
look at uh the child chart to figure out
if it's busy and the child component
like you know how how do you figure that
out? Uh so that's a little more you know
something you've got to build on top.
>> Yeah.
>> Yeah. But that that is the idea.
Okay. Uh
managing state versus state. I don't
remember what I was. It's been two
weeks. What was I talking about here?
Okay. Yeah, I remember what I was
talking about. Okay. So, remember we
talked about the data model there being
a local data model that's just meant for
the session of the state chart. I've got
10 different sessions of the same state
chart. They've each got their own
private data that they can work with,
right?
Uh something I've seen AI doing and I
suspect people will also do as well is
is either is is misusing
uh the local data model to save things
that shouldn't be kind of permanently
stored in that local session memory.
Right? So uh uh good examples of things
that you might want to put in local data
are is things that must survive across
states that live for arbitrary amounts
of time. Right? So for example in that
routing system remembering what route
they were trying to go to. Uh the
dialogue is going to pop right
remembering that through a potential
sequence of UI operations and such where
there might be multiple steps or
something. Uh same same with the um
sorry let's say you've loaded a bookmark
and you're not logged in yet, right? And
you you want to go to this accounting
report, right? Uh but it turns out your
password's expired, right? I'm going to
take you through a whole sequence of
steps to reset your password that are a
whole bunch of different routes and I
need to remember once you actually get
logged in where did you want to go now?
Right? That's a good use for this this
local data store, right?
Um, you might you might want to be
storing like I don't know accumulated
wizard answers isn't a good good one
necessarily because we would be using
rad forms and the wizard would actually
be one form with multiple steps. So folk
state would be storing that which
actually technically in the folk data
model is part of the data model. So I
guess I guess maybe that is true
accumulated wizard answers right I'm
actually remembering that data over
time. uh retry counters. Let's say
you've got some network mechanism in
your state chart that's trying to make
some operation but make it more robust.
So the operation fails and it it's going
to try again but you want sort of
exponential back off. You want to know
how many times you tried. You need to
remember where you're at. So that's
great for that local data. So so sort of
think about like almost like class based
that class-based ID uh idea of I've got
some data. I need to keep track of
something. Uh, okay. Where it's not
good,
uh, oneshot values. So, so for example,
uh, a loading flag. Uh, you're probably
better off modeling that as a state,
right? You have this asynchronous idea
of I'm I'm waiting for something to
happen that happens at some arbitrary
time in the future. You should actually
move to a state that can handle the
various problems that might happen
there. Right? There could be a network
error. There could be a whatever, right?
Uh your response could be malformed.
There all sorts of things you might need
to handle. Probably better off having a
state. Uh something I've seen AI do is
is using
uh local data to save a computation
that is only then used in a transition
cond expression
immediately.
Um,
do I have a do I have that example like
this? Uh,
um, well, no, this isn't the bad
example.
>> That's a good
>> that's a good example, right? Saving the
URL, redirecting later. Uh, here we go.
Uh, on entry assign should retry
some value. And then the con is just
look at should retry. Just just move
this logic into here.
Right? That's it's kind of a a silly
thing to store in local data uh because
you you can compute it very quickly in
the condition itself,
right? So so you're just better better
off doing that. Um same with like store
a loading flag. Well, you're probably
going to be in loading anyway, right?
duplicating duplicating what should be
in a state or is in a state in the data
model just for I don't know convenience
or something right you're going to pull
it out in the UI and say is loading true
pull out the configuration
right so so be a little careful about
what you use this local data for
um yeah so if it if
yeah if you've got a state that can just
be computed, then it's not really a
state. It's a derived value for like a
condition. So like in our subscription
state chart, um when we're trying to
figure out if if someone uh uh like what
you know what state we should move them
to, there's a choice node that right has
conditions that are actually expressions
that side effect and go look at the
database etc. We don't have a
pre-transition that runs some stuff and
sticks all that in the data model,
right? that would be denormalizing
what's in Daytonic.
So if we can go and fetch it as a
condition, it doesn't make sense to have
like a pre-step an on entry that says,
"Okay, let's go to Daytonic and look it
all up and put it in the local state
chart." That local state chart data
lives forever.
You've now put values in there that were
true for a particular point in time that
aren't true forever. Right? There's a
mismatch in in lifetime of the value.
That that's actually I hadn't thought of
it that way before. That's actually the
best way to to state does it go in the
local data model,
right? It's a good idea to put it in the
local data model if it's okay for it to
be there permanently and its value will
sort of permanently be there uh or or
permanently be correct until such time
as it's either overwritten or deleted by
the model. So that that whole URL kind
of thing, like what URL did they load
the page with? Well, that's true
forever. You only ever use it once in
the chart.
uh but it's okay for it to be in the
data model and maybe when you apply it
you remove it and in fact my code does
uh remove that data item from the model
once it's it's done using it. So so yeah
think about that life cycle of the data
you're putting in local data. uh are you
keeping it for just the time period that
it makes sense? And if that time period
is kind of instantaneous, maybe you just
compute it.
And then they've got an example here of
a shopping cart, right? Uh modeling your
cart is empty, the cart has items, the
cart is over the limit as states is kind
of silly. Just keep track of how many
items are in the cart.
Right. Um and and that's that that's
enough, right? Having that in the data
model is enough to get everything right.
And in fact, that's probably uh at least
in the folkloral case, this particular
example is it's in the folk app state,
right? You don't you don't need to keep
track of it as individual states in the
state chart. It's already information
that exists
um as just part of the the regular data
model.
Okay. Um,
all right. We'll do a little bit of
this. I'm not going to talk about the
routing system specifically. The Tao app
doesn't use the state charts routing
system. The Brazil app is trying to, but
it's not completely stabilized yet. So,
I don't want
>> The best part.
>> What's that best part?
>> It's the best part.
>> Yeah, it's it's is homework. Uh, feel
free to go look at the the Tao expansion
project and and see how the the routing
looks there.
>> I can talk about it if you guys want
later on.
>> Yeah, it's just get we're getting a
little long here. We've been on here for
how many hours now? We have three
>> since 10 a.m. So, yeah.
>> Yeah. So, I'm I'm I'm getting really
tired and I usually don't get tired when
training.
I'm sure I'm sure some of you are just
like, "Oh my god,
my brain hurts.
There's a lot of information to absorb
in one sitting."
So the folk integration is really
modeled after the UI state machines
patterns that that I had originally
designed for it. So state charts
themselves, we're we're kind of done
with them. That that's how state charts
work. Those are the elements you have.
uh you can mix and match, you can
compose, you can invent nodes of your
own that are composits of those you know
primitive elements uh to great effect uh
you know when you when you see the
actual here let's let's just I said I
wasn't going to talk about it but let's
just go look at it where's the routing
at which name space go root or system
is it this one no
you muted help me out where'd you put
the routing
root.
>> I don't know if it's merged in yet what
I did.
>> Oh, here it is.
>> I know you're in the wrong branch, but
yeah,
>> I'm on the wrong branch, but this is
basically what it looks like. Um,
so, uh,
>> sucks. Like what you're seeing here
sucks like you haven't rebased and I
don't like this one. Made it much.
>> Well, all right. Give me a second. See
if I've got any changes here.
Master is good enough in my opinion.
Sorry.
This better
or did you put it in root?
Looks the same to me. Oh, I haven't
pulled the state changed a bit. But um
the state chart changed a bit. Wait,
it's in the same place where you were
at, but you can show like the routing UI
and the state, you know, like
>> show
I I was I was mainly interested in just
showing what this looks like. So, so
these are custom states that we've
designed into the routing system. These
are invocation states that will invoke
the state chart that's colllocated on
this target. So, this guy's going to
have a state chart that it'll invoke
um uh when it's entered.
Uh and so this gives you a way to just
say here here are my routes and here are
the components that make up those routes
and oh by the way here's a here's a you
know a thing that I run on entry or on
exit because these are just states. So I
can put you know an on entry handler
here etc. Right?
So uh and these custom nodes just do
nothing more than emit uh a parallel or
state based on whether or not the
parallel option is true. Here node with
props with an ID. This is an open map so
you can put customized properties on
these and find them later. An on entry
that does things like establishes the uh
route parameters from the URL. uh
initializes the route, updates the
parent query dynamically so that you
don't have to do any complex query
composition manually in your UI. Um and
keeps track of uh what what idents are
currently on screen.
This this remembers I think which ident
you're on and this forgets oh no this is
the remember right. Um so internally
it's using the data model to remember
what's currently on screen. Uh because
you could have parallel regions where
there are multiple things on screen like
uh say a master uh uh slave master
whatever they call it like you've got
the list on the left and the forum on
the right kind of thing both things are
active simultaneously like a reports
running with a forum. uh that would be
that would be a a use case for a
parallel
node where you want both to be active at
the same time.
Um
and so this is a good example of, you
know, a fairly complicated thing that
you would just have to write and repeat
and repeat and repeat and repeat
throughout your entire application
turned into a single, you know, line of
usage at the state chart level. And
since most of that's executable content,
this still draws pretty nicely because
it's just a single note. It's just a
single statement.
And then I showed you the routes
implementation earlier. This is actually
emitting a transition that can go
directly to any one of
the the targets that exist down here.
So, you know, you can basically make it
so that you could type a whole lot less,
right? Because you've got closure. It's
just a data structure. Make a function
that returns better data structures.
>> And we're also handling the logging in
and logging out, which I think works in
the state chart.
>> Yeah. Exactly. Like like the whole
startup, logging in, getting the
configuration, figuring out who you are.
Yep.
>> Yeah.
>> It's lovely. So, so this whole this
whole mess of which I keep whining about
into Tao, right, that that was made over
the years of component did mount and
side effect this and side effect that at
the UI layer just evaporates like the
code is just pure just show me what's on
the what's in the database just show it
um all the logic of getting set up
waiting for things to happen etc uh can
all be in the state chart
There is one particular topic uh I don't
really want to talk I mean you guys are
are you all familiar with the actors
aliases idea from UISM maybe not all of
you are
um in fact I know some of you aren't so
let me talk about it this was an
invention that I made with UI state
machines because what I wanted was state
machines that could work with fulcrum
and I wanted the state machines to be
reusable
because the primary thing that I was
going to use UISM for I wrote it in
order to write RAD. So that was the
sequence of invention, right? So I had
fulcrutations. It's like all right, when
we get into this complex logic,
mutations aren't enough, right? You get
into the whole callback hell. Like it
doesn't solve the problem as well as I
hoped it would.
uh it abstracts away the full stack
nature which is nice but you still have
this mess of I have to write a mutation
that invokes a mutation and on result
and on error and mess right so I wanted
a state machine that could control a
report or a form and most things are
reports and forms and they have the same
logic needs right you're going to
validate the form you're going to figure
out if it's dirty right all that stuff's
normalized in form state there's no
reason to keep repeating the logic over
and over and over and over, right? I was
tired of it. This why RAD got invented
is I don't want to keep writing this
boiler plate. It's stupid.
But if I write a set of logic, the logic
needs to know which component, which
form, which form and state am I working
on? What fields does it have? That kind
of thing. Well, folk already had you
colllocating the field declarations on
the component. It already had the query.
It had all the data for the form. It
just didn't have any of the logic. So
the idea behind actors is just to say
here's the class and here's its ident
so that I know which thing I'm working
on dynamically at startup time. I can
start a state machine or a state chart
and tell it your report is this guy.
Your dialogue for confirming things is
this guy. And then the user of the state
charter state machine can plug in their
UI and reuse the state machine over and
over and over again. And then internally
in your logic when you want to read or
write data you do it with respect to the
actors. And because that can be annoying
all right I need to say the actor report
busy flag is true.
Then it's nice just to be able to
specify aliases. This was just a
syntactic convenience. make an alias
called busy that means the busy flag on
the actor that's the report.
That's all it is. It's just a way to
declare at startup time I want this
abstract concept of a particular
component
that I can go look at its component
options because I know its class. So I
can look at its query. I can look at its
right I can look at any of the options I
want to plop on there. The form options
what form fields are here etc. And I
know where it lives in the state map
because it's normalized with its item.
And then the aliases just give me a
quick handle on the common things that I
expect your UI to implement uh to work
with the particular machine.
Cool, huh? I was really proud of this
invention. This this like this this is
what makes RAD easy and possible with
just a single macro like defc form. Same
logic. Uh when you do that deficum when
you start
uh a form you're starting it on the
class which assigns it to be this actor
the actor form and then the logic just
works.
Okay. Um we already talked about the two
data layers in Fulcro's data model. The
local data is stored here in state chart
session ID and then the session ID of
the particular running state chart.
If you want to see the configuration
uh
is that in that same place
you have the session and the local ID.
This is the session data. You have to
have this in your focal query.
So let me let me expand on that. So
Fulcro
lets you treat your application as if
you're doing key frame renders, right?
You change the app database, it figures
out what to redraw, as if it's doing a
render from root. From an optimization
perspective, that's a horrible idea,
right? Actually rerendering the entire
DOM on every transaction is expensive.
We wouldn't want to do that even with
even with with uh React doing the VDOM
optimizations. You still don't want to
necessarily do that on a really complex
UI. You only want to rerender the things
that have actually changed.
By default, defc
adds in a minimization,
not with hooks, but without hooks. You
don't don't set hooks to true. It adds
in a a minimalization of the props at
each render at the component layer. And
if the props match what it saw last
time, it doesn't render. It skips that
one. It tells React this doesn't need
refresh. So React can just skip that
whole sub tree.
As a result, if you want to see the
state charts config changing over time,
you need to get it into the components
props. The only way to get into the
components props is to add it to the
query.
So if you want to see the configuration
changing in the UI component, you need
to add this ident to your component
props, which if you don't know the
session ID, you can just do it with a
single quote. That's a regular single
quote underscore and you'll get the
whole table, which is actually cheap to
query because it just pulls the
immutable map and sticks it on your
props. Uh, and as long as those props
change, you'll refresh. Now, that might
over render your component, but unless
you're experiencing an actual rendering
performance problem, who cares?
So, that's usually what I what I
recommend adding to the query is just SC
session ID with a with a a quoted
underscore.
Uh, if you need to see the the
configuration of the state chart
changing during render, right? So, if
you're if you're basing what you're
rendering on which state you're in, you
need to do that.
Any questions on that bit?
>> Nope. Okay. Think
>> it would be useful to have like in the
dev thing for the Brazil to see the
routing stuff right somewhere in the dev
menu.
>> Oh, certainly. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah.
When you've got that top bar that's
going to show which route they're on,
that component is going to want to query
for and it's going to use the session
ID. We have a well-known session ID for
that routing state chart. Uh so it's
just going to include just that one
session ID in its query so it can see
the states changing so it can render
which route is active in the menus right
absolutely
>> I need to add that
there's a helper function uh for this if
you know the session ID that you can
just use in the query expression I
forget the exact it's like it's like uh
uh state chart session ident
it's in the
Um there's also a local data uh the
local data I think is SC is it local I
think it's local data session ID
something like that.
>> Yeah. Uh you can find these just by
looking in your focal state map and in
inspect.
Um
okay.
All right. The other thing that I
recently solved and this was required to
get routing to be good on the front end.
This was this was a big realization.
This was huge. Oh my god, this was so
huge. Um
uh so I I've written this state chart
routing thing like three times
and the first two times it was just
complete garbage. I was just so unhappy
with it. And uh I sat down to have a
conversation with Claude to see if I
could, you know, you know, think my way
through it in a conversation. And as I
started to type the prompt, this
solution hit me and I was just like, "Oh
yeah, Claude has to implement this for
me." So instead of asking it, having a
conversation with it, uh, I asked it to
implement this particular thing. Um,
which it did. Uh, and I'm pretty sure
it's right. Like it seems to be working.
We I had it write tons and tons of
tests. uh I've not used it super
heavily, but I know there are other
users out there that are already using
the routing system and nobody's
complained about this particular feature
of state charts.
So in recent versions of the state
charts library what I did was I realized
that when you're in the server so so
like the um uh in our in our DTO system
and we've got some say like onboarding
or subscription that's actually
this this subscription state chart is
kind of the quintessential
uh example because it's got just so many
side effecty things that happen.
This choice node,
uh, not that one. Where's the Oh, there
it is. This choice node right here.
Right. Uh, I'm I'm hitting this unpaid
condition, which is going to check to
see if the plan is paid for, and if so,
go to state paid. Otherwise, I'm going
to go to the grace period state. Um, so
so this condition right here, plan paid
for, has to do IO. It goes and it hits
it grabs a database and it hits this
which runs this period 4 which runs a
query, right? Uh which gets all these
periods and then reverse map blah blah
blah, right? It does a bunch of work.
The state chart sits right here waiting
for it to do that work.
This is actually very very nice. Right?
I'm sitting here waiting for the answer
to plan paid for and it might take
several seconds and that's okay. The
thread running this event's just going
to block and when I get the answer I
will do the right thing in the state
chart. Okay, move to JavaScript land.
There is no blocking IO. It's impossible
to write this chart this way. Uh uh
because the expressions this question
mark if it needs to do IO it's async. It
cannot block the thread.
And so there's no way to write this
chart this way. What you have to do
instead is write a bunch of intermediate
states
where you schedule the getting of the
IO, go into a state where you're waiting
for the result of the IO and then
evaluate it. Right? It doubles or
triples the number of states you need to
do anything reasonable. And that is is
the realization I had about the routing
being ugly.
So, here's a use case in routing where
I've got to do IO, but it's going to
cause me problems.
Let's say I've got a route uh really
simple. I've got a logged in route. The
login in order to get into the logged
route, I've got to call check session,
which is a load at least. That's the
minimum, right? I've got to go retrieve
the user's current session asynchrony
right there. So now I have to have
another state
that puts you in sort of a waiting for
are they logged in kind of thing. Right?
Now think about the the whole I'm trying
to go to some accounting report that's
nested in some place in the routing.
Right? I've got to get into three
different states and they all have
potential to need loading something and
they all have the need
to to have the stuff that's above them
happen first, right? I've got to resume
the session before I can start loading
the uh company information and I need
the company information before I can
start loading the accounting, right?
Etc. There's like a sequence of loads.
So imagine this tree of routing and I
need to go through this sequence of
steps synchronously in a system that
only allows IO via asynchrony.
The state chart's going to be a
nightmare and I'm not going to be able
to use clean on entry onexit handlers to
say on entry load this thing with the
implication that I don't do the next on
entry until the load is done.
Right? I want the ability to write the
state chart as if
the expressions in the state chart
block.
Does everybody follow the problem?
>> Yeah.
>> I want this plan paid for in the in the
front end to be able to do a folk load
and sit right here until the folk load's
done. If it has to move to the next
state, if the state chart has to keep
processing because the expression didn't
block, then I'm screwed. So, as I was
starting to write this explanation to
Claude, it hit me, oh, I just want to
park. I want to park instead of block,
right? Parking is where I let go of the
thread, but it remembers where the
thread was running so that when the
result is there, I continue from there.
It's like a continuation. That's what I
want. and asynchronous constructs
already exist in closure to make that
relatively easy to code. So what I
needed was to to write remember remember
earlier when I said I was showing you
all the protocols
um
we were looking at these these protocols
and I said the processor is pluggable
because you know I was thinking backward
compatibility forward compatibility.
Guess what?
If you implement a processor that parks
instead of blocks, you can plug it in.
So I had Claude write a new
implementation
of that algorithm with async support,
async parking.
Uh, I think there was one minor but
compatible change to the overall
structure of the library
which I was just like I was so happy.
Anytime you can do this kind of like
serious internal restructuring kind of
thing without breaking users, it's
amazing. Like think about that. We just
added a whole new implementation that
still follows the exact semantics of
state charts, but when you return a
promise from an expression, you can
choose the block.
That's pretty cool.
>> Yeah, it is.
>> So, so that was the realization. And so
now there is an async execution engine
that you can select. It still defaults
to the non-async because that's right.
Right? I don't want to break existing
users. But if you install focal state
charts with async true
uh then you have support for
uh parking in the execution engine but
it's selectable even then. Uh so there
are asynchronous fulcr operations
uh where this will block
and then schedule these events but
you'll sit here on this on entry until
this load is done and then it'll send
the event right or
uh if you use the older operation which
I did not delete even with async true
this one doesn't return a promise and so
the state chart immediately continues.
So if you want to continue using the I
want to model each thing as a state, you
can still do that because both are
actually useful.
Routing really wants the ability to
block because you're trying to establish
a nested hierarchy of states into the
configuration
and the sideffecting of loading needs to
block that establishment as you go for
the for the routing, you know, state
chart to look clean and to be easy to
reason about.
But in some cases, you actually do want
to model the IO through a sequence of
steps because of whatever, right?
Specific kinds of handling or whatever
you might want to do. Uh like you just
might want to spell it out. Uh so you
can do both.
Um
the the and that brings to mind the the
one disadvantage with this particular
thing is that an an asynchronous op
since it blocks the chart right here in
the UI while this load is running. You
won't see the state chart moving. It'll
be it'll be stuck on whatever this state
is that this on entry is is currently
running and the configuration
will be in transition inside of the
internals of the state chart.
Now we have load markers, right? So you
can still make an observable thing
happen in the UI based on, right,
Fulcro's load management system where
you can do load markers where that
modifies something in state that you can
then render on the UI. Uh but you're
you're not going to model the the
loading
concept as a particular state that you
can view from the UI. So that's the
trade-off, right? When you do these
asynchronous side effects, you block the
chart. It's not moving. It's got an
intermediate in-memory
state happening thing happening that
until the micro steps are done, it won't
write the the state chart value back to
the storage. So that's the main thing to
to know about that. Do I have a
question?
Um if the promise fails is like is it a
custom event or is it the default you
know error mechanism that is triggered
as if the expression had raised an error
>> good question I don't remember and that
may be that may be underdefined it may
not be well defined
um the way for example load is modeled
is uh it's it's going to finish some way
shape or form like the the promise
itself is going to be satisfied with
either the network request succeeded or
the network request had an error. So the
promise is going to be fulfilled.
Um
in the case of of returning a
uh a promise all you're guaranteed is
that the the um when the promise is done
in some way, shape or form that you'll
unblock.
I I I I think I left it up to you to
figure out what you actually do
uh from there.
>> Okay.
>> Right. So, the whole promise catch that
that kind of thing. I I I may have put
something in, but to be honest, I
honestly don't remember. uh because the
primary use case I have are these use
cases with load and and transact where
we're already kind of just assuming
uh the mechanism itself is going to
succeed. So the promise just can't fail.
a failure is a result for the promise
but we could make it if I didn't we
could make it so that a promise failure
uh uh could be considered an expression
error and the expression error right
that already has a well- definfined
uh behavior in the state charts right if
there's an expression error you fire uh
an an error uh event automatically
Yeah, absolutely.
>> But yeah, I honestly don't I don't know
if we're doing that
uh at this point. It's such a new it's a
new enough feature that if we decided
that semantic is what should be
implemented, we could do it.
>> Okay, I'm done. That's that's all the
stuff that I wanted to talk about.
Uh I don't know how many hours are left
in the day there.
Two or three.
Did we finish the talk on time?
>> I think about 3 or 4 3:30.